¬ ============================
¬ Generic Events
¬ ============================

{WELCOME_TO_RIS_TITLE}RTR Imperium Surrectum
{WELCOME_TO_RIS_BODY}Welcome to RIS! This mod was made to provide you with a far more challenging, historically immersive game.\n\nMost factions start with a negative income. Cities provide less income and armies cost more than in vanilla. Use your troops, don't let them grow idle! Farms and mines buildings provide most income, make sure to build up your cities to avoid imperial overstretch. Recruitment in cities requires both factional 'recruitment' as well as military infrastructure buildings.\n\nNote that some enemy cities will spawn garrisons when under siege. AI factions receive extra income and better upgraded armies. \n\nRemember, the mod is balanced for Hard/Hard difficulty. \nIf your unit cards appear as peasants, please go to the graphics settings, and change the unit color scheme from vibrant to realistic. \nIf you have any other issues or face bugs, please go to the RIS Discord to report it and get help: discord.gg/ris-mod \n\nRome was not built in a day, defeats are only setbacks. Good luck, General!

{AOR_REFORMS_TITLE}Military innovations have arrived!
{AOR_REFORMS_BODY}Over recent decades, many peoples have been inspired to adopt new weapons or to innovate their combat styles through encounters with foreigners on the battlefield. From this moment onwards, they will be available to you as AoR units when you conquer their homelands across the board!

¬ ============================
¬ Faction Specific Events
¬ ============================

¬ ============================
¬ Rome
{REFORM_ROMANS_JULII_TITLE}A New Man: Gaius Marius
{REFORM_ROMANS_JULII_BODY}In the long years of campaigning under him, the troops of Gaius Marius have become professional soldiers. This also means that all Roman foot soldiers have been armoured in a uniform way. Furthermore, they are now carrying their equipment themselves (hence the nickname muli mariani, Marius' mules), but fare more importantly, will serve for 16 years on average and receive a land allottment for their retirement afterwards. This will certainly bring about problems...\n\nThe troop types available for recruitment now reflect the structure of this new professional army. Check the recruitment scroll to view the details.\n\n

¬ ============================
¬ Carthage
{REFORM_CARTHAGE_1_TITLE}Xanthippos Reforms
{REFORM_CARTHAGE_1_BODY}Carthage always to a large extent relied on mercenaries, strangers, to fight its wars. Over time, military innovations in the Greek world, such as the adoption of Thureos-bearing infantry, therefore also became reflected in its roster. This reform, situated in 255 BC, makes some of these new units available for recruitment, following the retraining of a Carthaginian army by Xanthippos the Spartan. Check the recruitment scroll to view their details.\n\n

{REFORM_CARTHAGE_2_TITLE}Barcid Reforms
{REFORM_CARTHAGE_2_BODY}The Libyans have undergone major transformations during the course of the wars with the Romans, or the Punic Wars as they are often known. Under the influence of these repeated military encounters, many of their techniques (and much of their equipment) started to be 'borrowed' from their Roman foe. The Libyans moved more towards the Roman way of fighting, and although nowhere near a manipular army, they definitely separated more from the Greek influence of their predecessors. During Hannibal's Italian campaign, most famously, many of his soldiers were re-equiped with Roman weapons looted from the battlefield.\n\nThe reform unit available for recruitment now reflects this development. Check the recruitment scroll to view its details.\n\n

¬ ============================
¬ Macedon
{REFORM_ANTIGONID_I_TITLE}Macedonian Reform I
{REFORM_ANTIGONID_I_BODY}Hail, Basileios! In recent years, our army has been strengthened by ferocious mercenaries from a wide variety of foreign peoples. Some of them, such as the Trallians, have even been enlisted in your royal guard! These developments have resulted in our adopting new military strategies and equipment, which are represented through a number of reformed units that have now become available for recruitment. Make sure to check the recruitment scroll to view their details!\n\n

{REFORM_ANTIGONID_II_TITLE}Macedonian Reform II
{REFORM_ANTIGONID_II_BODY}Hail, Basileios! Over the last decades, we have faced numerous enemies in battle. Unfortunately, not always with the great success that might be expected from the only true heirs of the great Alexander... Now, however, our engineers have come up with a brilliant new weapon that will surely allow to try and turn the tides of war into our favour: the kestros sling! Some of our light infantry have already been equipped with this dangerous new weapon. Make sure to check the recruitment scroll to view their details!\n\n

¬ ============================
¬ Ptolemies
{REFORM_PTOLEMAIC_I_TITLE}Ptolemaic Reform I
{REFORM_PTOLEMAIC_I_BODY}Hail, pharaoh! Macedonian and Greek manpower is hard to come by, and the everlasting war against the Seleucids and our own rebellious subjects is draining our small pool of true Hellenes... Fortunately, the local Egyptian population is swelling, and they are eager to fight! If we provide them with a small plot of land to sustain themselves, and train them in our superior Macedonian tradition, we can draft thousands of these ‘Machimoi’ (warriors) into our army. These men are willing to die for you, and for the Ptolemaic Empire. The bravest might even form ‘Epilektoi’ regiments and could guard our court! Beware, though, that they do not get too powerful, as rumours of  the local’s strive for independence have been snuffed out within the ranks of these new recruits… Make sure to check the recruitment scroll to view the details of these new troops that have now become available for recruitment, and to learn all about their historical background!

{REFORM_PTOLEMAIC_II_TITLE}Ptolemaic Reform II
{REFORM_PTOLEMAIC_II_BODY}Hail, pharaoh, glorious victor, you who have smitten rebels and foes, making them crawl and grovel on the scorched earth in well-deserved misery! Egyptian natives joined the ranks of our armies as brothers in arms, only to turn their pikes against us in a most horrible form of betrayal. Hard fighting subdued any kind of resistance that might have persisted among the treacherous natives, who would never dream of resisting their pharaoh’s command again in future. Those troops surviving the purge, receiving our most benign amnesty, have once more become available for recruitment to join our ranks with sword and mount. These Machimoi will be useful to police our kingdom and eradicate the final patches of native resistance, but can also bolster the ranks of our army on the field of battle against foreign invaders if need arises. Make sure to check the recruitment scroll to view their details!\n\n

{REFORM_PTOLEMAIC_III_TITLE}Ptolemaic Reform III
{REFORM_PTOLEMAIC_III_BODY}Hail, pharaoh! Following the reforms of Polykrates, our Therapeia guard cavalry has been retrained to become more efficient in battle. They have also been re-equipped with sturdy bronze muscle cuirasses and plumed helmets, a wonderful sight to behold. Inspired by the Cretans, Thracians and Gauls arriving in Polykrates' wake, part of our men have been trained in their fighting style as Neo-Cretans and Thorakitai. Combining the best of old and new, our reinvigorated forces will surely go on to dominate all of Alexanders' conquests and much beyond! Make sure to check the recruitment scroll to view their details!\n\n

¬ ============================
¬ Seleucids
{REFORM_SELEUCID_TITLE}Seleucid Reforms I
{REFORM_SELEUCID_BODY}Greetings, mighty Basileios, may you live long and prosper, Agathe Tyche. Our Macedonian soldiers are the best in the world, sons of the divine Herakles themselves, worthy of Alexander the demigod. Yet, sometimes us mortals have to change, and it seems that now a new type of armour has become available, which will protect the Thorax (chest) of our soldiers. Allow us to retrain our men to fight as Thorakitai and you will see how effective our Greek armour is. Long live the dynasty of Seleukos! Make sure to check the recruitment scroll to view their details!\n\n

{REFORM_SELEUCID_II_TITLE}Seleucid Reform II
{REFORM_SELEUCID_II_BODY}Hail Basileios, we are well and hope to find you well, Agathe Tyche. A storm from the east has ravaged our lands. The Barbarians our philosophers call Parnoi have ruthlessly attacked our cities, stolen our cattle and enslaved good Greek citizens. But, there is good news, Zeus Olympios has led your generals to victory! They have learnt that the enemy uses a cavalry clad in metal plates, which we now call Kataphraktoi. It seems sensible to copy this style of fighting, so if you agree, mighty king, you may recruit our own regiment of these beasts now. Make sure to check the recruitment scroll to view their details!\n\n

{REFORM_SELEUCID_III_TITLE}Seleucid Reform III
{REFORM_SELEUCID_III_BODY}Praise you Basileios, with good wishes from your people, Agathe Tyche. The Barbarians who call themselves Rhomaioi are ever expanding their realm. They are now threatening your grand kingdom, and the time has come to counter their endless swordsmen with a new weapon. Five thousand of our Argyraspides have been re-armed with chainmail shirts, the big oval shields of the Barbarians, straight swords, and javelins. In difference to the Rhomaioi, they are professional soldiers and will cut through them like a Xiphos through hot Syrian butter. King Seleukos be praised! Make sure to check the recruitment scroll to view their details!\n\n

¬ ============================
¬ Pergamon
{REFORM_PERGAMON_TITLE}Pergamene Reforms
{REFORM_PERGAMON_BODY}Chaire, Basileios, your friends greet you! By Athena, you have done well to consolidate our kingdom. Our borders are now not just bound by the Kaikos river below Pergamon, but many of the Mysians also stand under your control. Accordingly, we have integrated light Mysian infantry into our army - they are now ready to be recruited from cities across the kingdom. Make sure to check the recruitment scroll to view their details!\n\n

{REFORM_PERGAMON_II_TITLE}Pergamene Reforms II
{REFORM_PERGAMON_II_BODY}Chaire, Basileios, your friends greet you! How far we have come! When Athena raises her eyes to look across your realm, she sees bountiful valleys, bustling ports, mighty fortresses and flourishing cities. Many of the inhabitants of this kingdom are Mysians, and they have now adopted the equipment of our neighbours, the Seleucids. At the same time, we have created a new regiment of royal pikemen, the Agema, to further strengthen our forces. This new model army will be unstoppable, and your glory will stretch to the ends of Asia. Make sure to check the recruitment scroll to view their details!\n\n

¬ ============================
¬ Sparta
{REFORM_SPARTA_TITLE}The military reforms of Kleomenes III
{REFORM_SPARTA_BODY}After the success of Alexander and his successors, to which the Greek city states found no answer, the latter began to consider to retrain their Hoplites to fight as Macedonian style pikemen. The number of Homoioi had fallen to a mere 700 by the middle of the 3rd century BC, a number so small that it made an effective Macedonian phalanx with its depth of 12 or 16 ranks almost impossible. To solve the lack of manpower, Kleomenes had 2000 members of the lower strata of Spartan society, some of them former citizens (Hypomeiones), enfranchised, along with 2000 or 2500 Peroikoi and mercenaries. They received the social status of Neodamodeis, new citizens (Plutarch, Life of Kleomenes 11, 3). Most of them were equipped as Macedonian phalangites, though Ray (Hellenistic Land Battles 2020, p. 76-78) speculates that some of the Spartiates and other Hoplites retained their traditional equipment.\n\nThe troop types available for recruitment now reflect the structure of this new Macedonian-inspired army. Check the recruitment scroll to view the details.\n\n

¬ ============================
¬ Pontus
{REFORM_PONTUS_TITLE}Pontic Reforms I
{REFORM_PONTUS_BODY}Mighty lord of Cappadocia on the Pontos, Mithras praises you! Now that you have shown the Greeks on the coasts of the Pontos Euxeinos how powerful you are, the production of warships has begone. Our fleet has steadly grown and we have come to a point where we have decided to hire specialist soldiers who can fight aboard our triremes and penteres. Allow me to introduce this band of Galatians, they are brave and strong like all Gauls, but I have been assured that they do not fear the water and the waves. They are now ready to fight for you, my lord, and Pontos shall rule the waves. Make sure to check the recruitment scroll to view their details!\n\n

{REFORM_PONTUS_II_TITLE}Pontic Reforms II
{REFORM_PONTUS_II_BODY}Chaire, Basileios! Let Zeus and Mithras attest how splendidly you have led our kingdom, how great our wealth has become and how strong our army. We have followed your latest instructions and implemented the training of the terrible Macedonian phalanx, which has hurt us so profoundly in the past. No longer will Macedonian pikes defeat Pontic bravery, for now both former slaves and men born free will be able to fight back as phalangites themselves. Additionally, a new royal guard has been formed, which will make you proud: it is the Hypaspists of the demigod Alexander reborn! Cappadocia, Paphlagonia and the friendly Sea be praised! Make sure to check the recruitment scroll to view their details!\n\n

{REFORM_PONTUS_III_TITLE}Pontic Reforms III
{REFORM_PONTUS_III_BODY}Chaire, mighty Basileios, ruler of the land, mightiest of all the men in mother Asia! By Kybele and Athena, your greatness knows no bounds. The poets are already writing verses about your great victory against the western Barbarians. At the same time, our best engineers and officers have worked hard to reproduce the shiny armour of the Romaioi you spoke about. New troops that are equipped exactly like our foes are now available for recruitment and will ram home our advantage: Pontic courage! Make sure to check the recruitment scroll to view their details!\n\n

¬ ============================
¬ Bosporans
{REFORM_BOSPORAN_TITLE}Bosporan Reforms
{REFORM_BOSPORAN_BODY}Hail, Archon of Pantikapaion and Phanagoreia and Basileios of the Kimmerian Bosporos! A military innovation has occurred in your realm. Our horsemen have tested the oval Celtic shield, and they are pleased with the results. You may now recruit new cavalry units equipped with the Thureos from the royal barracks. May Herakles lead us to victory! Make sure to check the recruitment scroll to view their details!\n\n

{REFORM_BOSPORAN_II_TITLE}Bosporan Reforms II
{REFORM_BOSPORAN_II_BODY}Hail, strategos! Over time, our soldiers have encountered and slain many foes. This has also resulted in adopting new military strategies and equipment, that are represented through a number of reformed units that have now become available for recruitment. Make sure to check the recruitment scroll to view their details!\n\n

{REFORM_BOSPORAN_III_TITLE}Bosporan Reforms III
{REFORM_BOSPORAN_III_BODY}Hail, Basileios, Strategos Autokrator and Archon of the Greek cities on the Bosporos! You have led our men from victory to victory, and now, finally, the Black Sea yields when you speak. From beyond the great waves, military innovations have found their way into our land, and our melee infantry has been improved to fight ever more competently against those who cast covetous eyes on our rich lands. You may now recruit these men and lead us to yet another famous triumph!  Make sure to check the recruitment scroll to view their details!\n\n

¬ ============================
¬ Parthia
{REFORM_PARNI_TITLE}Parthian Reforms
{REFORM_PARNI_BODY}Hail, commander! Over time, our soldiers have encountered and slain many foes. This has also resulted in adopting new military strategies and equipment, that are represented through a number of reformed units that have now become available for recruitment. Make sure to check the recruitment scroll to view their details!\n\n

¬ ============================
¬ Getae
{REFORM_GETAE_TITLE}Getic Reforms
{REFORM_GETAE_BODY}Hail, my king! Over time, our soldiers have encountered and slain many foes. This has also resulted in adopting new military strategies and equipment, that are represented through a number of reformed units that have now become available for recruitment. Make sure to check the recruitment scroll to view their details!\n\n

¬ ============================
¬ Galatians
{REFORM_GALATIANS_TITLE}Galatian Reforms
{REFORM_GALATIANS_BODY}Hail, my king! Over time, our soldiers have encountered and slain many foes. This has also resulted in adopting new military strategies and equipment, that are represented through a number of reformed units that have now become available for recruitment. Make sure to check the recruitment scroll to view their details!\n\n

¬ ============================
¬ Selge
{REFORM_SELGE_TITLE}Selge Reforms I
{REFORM_SELGE_BODY}Esteemed Nobles of Selge, hear me out! We stand here, on our beautiful plain in the Pisidian mountains, independent, strong and unmatched in bravery. For generations, we have fought in the way of our forefathers, but the arrival of the horrible Galatians in Asia has changed much. We should not rest on our laurels, like our Spartan ancestors now do, but rather embrace the new and adopt the oval shield of the Galatians, so that Selgian soldiers shall prevail for ever more! For Selge! For Pisidia!!! Make sure to check the recruitment scroll to view their details!\n\n

{REFORM_SELGE_II_TITLE}Selge Reform II
{REFORM_SELGE_II_BODY}Esteemed council of Selge, today is a glorious day. Our officers have worked hard to make this day reality, and now here, in front of you, stand our first riders who can fight with a Hoplite shield from horseback. Selected as Ephebes when they were still young, they are now some of Pisidia's most renowned warriors, and they will terribly strike the enemy from their mounts. Protected by the great Greek round shield, they can deflect any missile the enemy can come up with. Selge is glorious! Make sure to check the recruitment scroll to view their details!\n\n

¬ ============================
¬ Achaian League
{REFORM_ACHAEA_TITLE}Achaian Reforms I
{REFORM_ACHAEA_BODY}"In the early summer of the year in which Agetas was strategos of the Aitolians (217 BC) [...] Aratos (of Sikyon) had found the mercenary forces of the Achaians disaffected and the cities not at all disposed to tax themselves for the purpose of maintaining them [...] (5) However, he made an appeal to the Achaians, and obtaining a decree on the subject, occupied himself actively with preparations for war. (6) The substance of the decree was as follows. They were to keep up a mercenary force of eight thousand foot and five hundred horse and a picked (epilektoi) Achaian force of three thousand foot and three hundred horse, (7) including five hundred foot and fifty horse from Megalopolis, all brazen-shielded, and an equal number of Argives." (Polybios of Megalopolis, Histories 5.91.1-8)\n\nMake sure to check the recruitment scroll to view their details!\n\n

{REFORM_ACHAEA_II_TITLE}Achaian Reforms II
{REFORM_ACHAEA_II_BODY}Philopoimen of Megalopolis: Assembly of the honourable Achaian Koinon, hear me!\n\nAchaians: Hear, hear!\n\nPhilopoimen: Dear Achaians, I know you have fought hard these past few years. You have defended your homes, you have marched into foreign lands, you have been starved, born incredible heat and scaled great heights.\n\nAchaians: Hear, hear!\n\nPhilopoimen: Yet, we can still improve our army. It is time to strengthen our infantry by giving the Thureophoroi better armour and by introducing the Macedonian phalanx!\n\nAchaians: <murmuring>\n\nPhilopoimen: There is more! <inhales deeply> Our horsemen have to learn how to ride and fight, and our ephebes have to be educated with the bow by Cretan experts. I know this will cost a huge effort, and a lot of money. But this is the way forward for Achaia. To survive, and thrive, we need to melt our jewels and silver tableware, and create armour and weapons. What do you think?\n\nAchaians: <silence>\n\nA young Ephebe steps forward: Achaians! I may be young, and I may not have fought as many battles as most of you. But I trust Philopoimen. He only wants the best for Achaia. Now, it is time for you to trust him as well!\n\nAnd thus, the Achaians began the great reform of their federal army. Make sure to check the recruitment scroll to view their details!\n\n

{REFORM_ACHAEA_III_TITLE}Achaian Reforms III
{REFORM_ACHAEA_III_BODY}Strategos of Achaia: We have bought Aspis shields to equip our horsemen with them. Any objections?\n\nAchaians: <remain silent>\n\nStrategos: And thus it is decided! Make sure to check the recruitment scroll to view their details!\n\n

¬ ============================
¬ Aetolian League
{REFORM_AETOLIA_TITLE}Aitolian Reforms
{REFORM_AETOLIA_BODY}Priest of Apollo: The Aitolian Assembly has assembled! To discuss: A proposal by the Kalydonians.\n\nAitolians: <murmuring>\n\nKalydonians: Brave men of Aitolia! We know you are the boldest warriors and best men of Greece!\n\nAitolians: Yaaahhh!!! Aitolia forever!\n\nKalydonians: Yet, ahem, we suggest an improvement for our army.\n\nAitolians: <murmuring>\n\nKalydonians: We brought with us new armour from Macedon, including Galatian chainmail, and shiny new Aspis shields that can be held by the rider of a horse. Allow us to equip our soldiers with these items, and we will be invincible!\n\nAitolians: <murmuring>\n\nThermonians: What does Apollo think?\n\nPriest: I will read the auspices!\n\nAitolians: By Apollo!\n\nPriest: ... I can see it. Yes...yes! Apollo wills it! We shall introduce the new regiments. I have spoken.\n\nAitolians: Yaaaahh! Aitolia forever! Make sure to check the recruitment scroll to view their details!\n\n

{REFORM_AETOLIA_II_TITLE}Aitolian Reforms II
{REFORM_AETOLIA_II_BODY}Priest of Apollo: Assembly of Aitolia, welcome the envoy of Knossos!\n\nAitolians: Hooray!\n\nKnossian envoy: <bows> The people and the council of the Knossians thanks you, men of Aitolia, for your friendship and support. We have come to pay our debts. These young men here are some of our most talented up-and-coming young archers. They will join your ranks and train your Ephebes how to use the bow like Apollo himself!\n\nAitolians: Hooray! Hooray! Long live Knossos! Make sure to check the recruitment scroll to view their details!\n\n

¬ ============================
¬ Athens
{REFORM_ATHENS_TITLE}Athenian Reforms I
{REFORM_ATHENS_BODY}Strategoi: Honourable Archontes and Demos of Athens, we, the strategoi, propose to equip some of our soldiers with the oval Thureos shield.\n\nDemos: What? Why? The shield of the Galatians, these treacherous Barbarians?\n\nStrategoi: It is large and cheap to produce, cheaper than the Aspis, so more men can fight and no extra tax is needed.\n\nDemos: No extra taxes and yet we will have more soldiers! Athena be praised, we agree!\n\nArchontes: It is decided! Make sure to check the recruitment scroll to view the new unit's details!\n\n

{REFORM_ATHENS_II_TITLE}Athenian Reforms II
{REFORM_ATHENS_II_BODY}Strategos Erechteus: Dear people of Athens! Hear me out! I know that you love your coins, but today you have to part with some of your drachmai, for we can strengthen our armies!\n\nDemos: Booo!!!\n\nErechtheus: Please, Athenians, we could use round shields and equip two different regiments of horsemen with them...\n\nDemos: BOOOOOOOOO!!!!\n\nStrategos Lysanias: Erechtheus is right, this new, flexible cavalry will be able to guard our mines, protect our farms and safeguard your families! If you want security, you need to vote for the Aspis! For our future! For Athens!\n\nDemos: FOR ATHENS!!!!! Make sure to check the recruitment scroll to view the new units' details!\n\n

¬ ============================
¬ Boiotian League
{REFORM_BOEOTIA_TITLE}Boiotian Reforms
{REFORM_BOEOTIA_BODY}Strategoi: Boiotians, hear us!\n\nAssembly: Booooo!!!! Losers! You brought shame on Boiotia!\n\nStrategoi: Hear us, hear us! We know you have heard about defeats...\n\nAssembly: SHAMEFUL!\n\nStrategoi: But Boiotia is strong! And we have a solution!\n\nAssembly: <murmuring>\n\nStrategoi: We will reform our army after the model of the Macedonians. Professional elite units and phalangites will march four our koinon, and march to victory!!!\n\nAssembly: Victory!!! Make sure to check the recruitment scroll to view their details!\n\n

{REFORM_BOEOTIA_II_TITLE}Boiotian Reforms II
{REFORM_BOEOTIA_II_BODY}Thebans: Why have we met today, Boiotian friends?\n\nTanagrans: We, the representatives of Tanagra, have a proposal.\n\nOther Boiotians: <murmuring>\n\nTanagrans: We have seen the Macedonians use Aspis shields for their cavalry. The large, round shield affords horsemen the ideal protection, and armed with kopis and spear, they will be unstoppable in melee.\n\nOrchomenians: But how much will it cost?\n\nTanagrans: Not that much, we already have many Aspis shields from our Hoplites, and the same goes for spears and Kopis swords. We can produce the necessary Linothorakes easily, one Linothorax can be produced for as little as 24 drachmae after the Athenian method...\n\nThebans: Bah, Athenians!\n\nAnthedonians: But it's cheap...\n\nOrchomenians: Let us vote!\n\nAnd thus the Boiotians voted to introduce Aspis bearing cavalry into their army. Make sure to check the recruitment scroll to view their details!\n\n

¬ ============================
¬ The Greek City States
{REFORM_GREEKS_TITLE}Greek Reforms
{REFORM_GREEKS_BODY}Hail, strategos! Over time, our soldiers have encountered and slain many foes. This has also resulted in adopting new military strategies and equipment, that are represented through a number of reformed units that have now become available for recruitment. Make sure to check the recruitment scroll to view their details!\n\n

¬ ============================
¬ Massalia
{REFORM_MASSALIA_TITLE}Massaliote Reforms I
{REFORM_MASSALIA_BODY}Strategos: Hear me, assembly of the six hundred noblest men of Massalia!\n\nAssembly: Hear, hear!\n\nStrategos: We are proud Massaliotes, much more elegant, intelligent and controlled than those barbaric Celts and Ligurians.\n\nAssembly: Hear, hear!\n\nStrategos: Yet, in order to defend ourselves, we should adopt their big, oval shield, the Thureos.\n\nAssembly: Hear, hear!\n\nStrategos: I have spoken.\n\nAssembly: We agree! For Massalia!\n\nStrategos: For Massalia! Make sure to check the recruitment scroll to view their details!\n\n

{REFORM_MASSALIA_II_TITLE}Massaliote Reforms II
{REFORM_MASSALIA_II_BODY}Strategoi: Noble six hundred of Massalia, we present you the new armour we have bought for our troops: breastplates, Gallic chainmail and metal reinforced Linothorakes. Our proud merchants have acquired these items to equip our Thureophoroi as Thorakitai, but they need to be reimbursed. Therefore, we ask for a leiturgia: Your money for the defense of Massalia!\n\nAssembly: <murmuring>\n\nStrategoi: Think of your children, think our our beautiful city, think of our elegant ships. We can protect all of that for a mere talent a year!\n\nAssembly: <murmuring>\n\nStrategoi: And finally, think of the pesky, stinking Barbarians we will defeat with their own armour!!!\n\nAssembly: LONG LIVE MASSALIA!!! Make sure to check the recruitment scroll to view these new unit's details!\n\n

¬ ============================
¬ Rhodes
{REFORM_RHODES_TITLE}Rhodian Reforms I
{REFORM_RHODES_BODY}Greetings, Strategos! Warfare beyond our Rhodian shore has changed, and it is time to adapt! A new, large, and oval-shaped shield has spread throughout Hellas and Asia. Its lightness makes it suitable for skirmishing but its size will also protect its bearer in a close formation. We should definitely make use of it on the battlefield! Make sure to check the recruitment scroll to view our new unit's details!\n\n

{REFORM_RHODES_II_TITLE}Rhodian Reforms II
{REFORM_RHODES_II_BODY}Messengers: Demos and Boule of the Rhodians, hear us out! We bring Aspis shields from Greece, to be carried by cavalry!\n\nPeople: WHAT!?\n\nMessengers: The time has come for our Hoplites to fight from horseback, as other Greeks are now doing. We must move with the times.\n\nPeople: <murmuring and mumbling>\n\nMessenger: Oh, strategoi, will you adopt our suggestions?\n\nStrategos 1: Rhodes is always at the forefront of change and innovation. I recommend to adopt the reform.\n\nStrategos 2: The demos alone rules, hence I will stay silent. Let us vote!\n\nAnd so, the people of Rhodes voted to introduce Aspis bearing horsemen into their army. Long live democracy!\n\n

¬ ============================
¬ Syracuse
{REFORM_SYRACUSE_TITLE}Syracusan Reforms I
{REFORM_SYRACUSE_BODY}Chaire, Basileios, ruler of Sikelia, first citizen of Syrakousai, the queen of all cities! You have brought wealth and happiness to your people, you have restored the temples and pacified the land. Now, the time has come to conquer beyond Sicily and retake what the mighty Dionysios once ruled: the ancient valleys and bountiful coasts of Italia. For this enterprise, we have retrained our cavalry to bear the big Thureos shield, and we have re-equipped some of our Thureophoroi foot soldiers with heavier armour. These new units will make our army even more powerful. May Apollo guide us to victory - Syrakousai forever! Make sure to check the recruitment scroll to view their details!\n\n

{REFORM_SYRACUSE_II_TITLE}Syracusan Reforms II
{REFORM_SYRACUSE_II_BODY}Archon, Strategos Autokrator, Basileus, the people of Syracuse praise you! You have been a great benefactor for our city and this island. Both in peace and war, you have evinced your divine qualities as a leader. Now, the newest gift to the Sikeliotes has arrived! Thanks to your generous funding of our military instructors, our Hoplites have learned how to fight on horseback. You may now recruit these men from our cities and towns - for the glory of Syracuse!\n\n

¬ ============================
¬ Massyli
{REFORM_MASSYLII_TITLE}Numidian Reforms
{REFORM_MASSYLII_BODY}Hail, my king! Over time, our soldiers have encountered and slain many foes. This has also resulted in adopting new military strategies and equipment, that are represented through a number of reformed units that have now become available for recruitment. Make sure to check the recruitment scroll to view their details!\n\n

¬ ============================
¬ Selge
{REFORM_SELGE_TITLE}Selge Reforms I
{REFORM_SELGE_BODY}Esteemed Nobles of Selge, hear me out! We stand here, on our beautiful plain in the Pisidian mountains, independent, strong and unmatched in bravery. For generations, we have fought in the way of our forefathers, but the arrival of the horrible Galatians in Asia has changed much. We should not rest on our laurels, like our Spartan ancestors now do, but rather embrace the new and adopt the oval shield of the Galatians, so that Selgian soldiers shall prevail for ever more! For Selge! For Pisidia!!! Make sure to check the recruitment scroll to view their details!\n\n

{REFORM_SELGE_II_TITLE}Selge Reform II
{REFORM_SELGE_II_BODY}Esteemed council of Selge, today is a glorious day. Our officers have worked hard to make this day reality, and now here, in front of you, stand our first riders who can fight with a Hoplite shield from horseback. Selected as Ephebes when they were still young, they are now some of Pisidia's most renowned warriors, and they will terribly strike the enemy from their mounts. Protected by the great Greek round shield, they can deflect any missile the enemy can come up with. Selge is glorious! Make sure to check the recruitment scroll to view their details!\n\n

¬ ============================
¬ Armenia
{REFORM_ARMENIA_TITLE}Armenian Reforms
{REFORM_ARMENIA_BODY}Hail, great king! Over time, our soldiers have encountered and slain many foes. This has also resulted in adopting new military strategies and equipment, that are represented through a number of reformed units that have now become available for recruitment. Make sure to check the recruitment scroll to view their details!\n\n

¬ ============================
¬ Arevaci
{REFORM_AREVACI_TITLE}Arevaci Reforms
{REFORM_AREVACI_BODY}Hail, my king! Over time, our soldiers have encountered and slain many foes. This has also resulted in adopting new military strategies and equipment, that are represented through a number of reformed units that have now become available for recruitment. Make sure to check the recruitment scroll to view their details!\n\n

¬ ============================
¬ Arverni
{REFORM_ARVERNI_TITLE}Arverni Reforms
{REFORM_ARVERNI_BODY}Hail, my king! Over time, our soldiers have encountered and slain many foes. This has also resulted in adopting new military strategies and equipment, that are represented through a number of reformed units that have now become available for recruitment. Make sure to check the recruitment scroll to view their details!\n\n

¬ ============================
¬ Trinovantes
{REFORM_TRINOVANTES_TITLE}Trinovantes Reforms
{REFORM_TRINOVANTES_BODY}Hail, great king! Over time, our soldiers have encountered and slain many foes. This has also resulted in adopting new military strategies and equipment, that are represented through a number of reformed units that have now become available for recruitment. Make sure to check the recruitment scroll to view their details!\n\n

¬ ============================
¬ Odrysian Kingdom
{REFORM_ODRYSIANS_TITLE}Odrysian Reforms
{REFORM_ODRYSIANS_BODY}Hail, my king! Over time, our soldiers have encountered and slain many foes. This has also resulted in adopting new military strategies and equipment, that are represented through a number of reformed units that have now become available for recruitment. Make sure to check the recruitment scroll to view their details!\n\n

¬ ============================
¬ Siraces
{REFORM_SIRACES_TITLE}Siraces Reforms
{REFORM_SIRACES_BODY}Hail, great chief! Over time, our soldiers have encountered and slain many foes. This has also resulted in adopting new military strategies and equipment, that are represented through a number of reformed units that have now become available for recruitment. Make sure to check the recruitment scroll to view their details!\n\n

¬ ============================
¬ Saka
{REFORM_SAKA_TITLE}Saka Reforms
{REFORM_SAKA_BODY}Hail, great chief! Over time, our soldiers have encountered and slain many foes. This has also resulted in adopting new military strategies and equipment, that are represented through a number of reformed units that have now become available for recruitment. Make sure to check the recruitment scroll to view their details!\n\n

¬ ============================
¬ Suebi
{REFORM_SUEBI_1_TITLE}Rise of the Warbands
{REFORM_SUEBI_1_BODY}The earliest known Germanic armies made effective use of formations and combined arms, but were nations in arms transferring communal cooperation onto the battlefield rather than professional militaries. Although effective in pitched battle, they could not campaign for long, which the permanent Roman legions exploited to their full advantage. Given their limited resources, the Germanic nations could not match those with standing armies of their own. Instead, their warlords began to surround themselves with smaller followings of professional fighters. The Germanic warband was born. Unlike other freemen, the men of the warbands were full-time soldiers and owed their upkeep to their liege. As a result, they were always available for campaign, and loyal to their warlord rather than their nation. Since warbands rarely exceeded a few hundred men, the increased reliance on such forces led to an overall reduction in the scale of Germanic warfare. Raids and skirmishes took preference over pitched battles. Moreover, the men of the warbands were essentially retainers competing for their lieges' favor. All combined to make the warbands more reliant on individual prowess rather than the cooperation that distinguished the freemen forces, who thenceforth only would be called upon as a last resort.\n\nWarband units are now available for recruitment. Check the recruitment scroll to view the details.\n\n

{REFORM_SUEBI_2_TITLE}Spoils of War
{REFORM_SUEBI_2_BODY}Initially, there was little difference in equipment between the warbands and the freemen militia. That changed over time. Successful raids and victorious battles against the Roman Empire yielded great spoils: Wealth and captives, but also arms. Since captured equipment passed from fathers to sons, and more was continually accumulated, the warbands became ever better armed and armored over the generations. Eventually, it became commonplace for members of Germanic warbands to sport equipment pieces of Roman, or even Sarmatian, origin. Often those complemented an otherwise Germanic kit. Yet, most important in the long run was the upswing in native Germanic weapons production that the spoils of war enabled. While an influx of wealth increased demand for better weaponry, captured craftsmen and equipment made it possible to reverse engineer enemy designs and produce Germanic versions. An especially striking adaptation was the angon: A Germanic version of the pilum, that closely resembled the Roman original and was used exactly the same way.\n\nAdvanced warband units are now available for recruitment. Check the recruitment scroll to view the details.\n\n

¬ ============================
¬ Baktria
{REFORM_BACTRIA_TITLE}Baktrian Reforms
{REFORM_BACTRIA_BODY}Hail, Basileios! Together with our independence from the Seleucid Empire, the migration of Greek and Macedonian military settlers has also come to an end. If we want to survive, we have to rely on the natives to bolster the ranks of our army. Its true core and elite, however, will always continue to be made up of the epigonoi, literally meaning 'offspring' or 'sons' of the proud Greeks originally settled here by Alexander and Seleukos. Years have past since the revolt in the late 3rd century BC. The epigonoi have by now slowly come to replace your regular hellenistic units. Make sure to check the recruitment scroll to view their details!\n\n

¬ ============================
¬ Kyrene
{REFORM_CYRENE_TITLE}Kyrenean Reforms
{REFORM_CYRENE_BODY}Mighty Basileios, autokrator of Kyrene, we praise you! Under the guidance of Zeus himself, you have established ourselves among the great realms of the world. The time has come to expand our phalanx and we have therefore decided to admit Libyans into these regiments, since the number of Greeks and Macedonians in Africa does not suffice. Additionally, we have adopted the big, oval Thureos shield from our Galatian mercenaries. Use these new weapons and units wisely. Make sure to check the recruitment scroll to view their details!\n\n

{REFORM_CYRENE_II_TITLE}Kyrenean Reforms II
{REFORM_CYRENE_II_BODY}Mighty Basileios, autokrator of Kyrene, by Zeus, be praised! You have led us to many a victory, like a true Hellenic heros. Now that our kingdom has grown to such an impressive size, we have enough money to set up two elite regiments with richly decorated armour and helmets. After the example of Alexander's Hypaspists and Arygraspides, phalanx and hoplite like elite regiments are now available for recruitment. Make sure to check the recruitment scroll to view their details!\n\n

¬ ============================
¬ Epeiros
{REFORM_EPIRUS_TITLE}Epirote Reforms
{REFORM_EPIRUS_BODY}Hail, Basileios! Over time, our soldiers have encountered and slain many foes. Among the barbarians we faced in Italy, we found cavalrymen hiding behind shields. Even if this practice was initially regarded as pure cowardice by our brave and noble warriors, over time we have come to see the merits of equipping our horsemen with an Aspis of their own. These new military strategies are represented by the Aspidophoroi, who have now become available for recruitment. Make sure to check the recruitment scroll to view their details!\n\n

¬ ============================
¬ Bithynia
{REFORM_BITHYNIA_TITLE}Bithynian Reforms I
{REFORM_BITHYNIA_BODY}Hail Basileios, your people wish you well, all is well with us, the Gods favour Bithynia. You have established an impressive kingdom, and your deeds will not be forgotten. But the time has come to improve our army even further, so that we may stop the Syrian monarchs and get rid of the pesky Attalids to our south. Our weapon smiths recommend adopting the Celtic Thureos shield, which is larger and wider than most of the shields we have used thus far, Greek or Thracian. We will equip some of the Hoplites as light infantry bearing these big shields, spears and javelins, and they shall be called Thureophoroi. They are now available for recruitment into the royal forces. Make sure to check the recruitment scroll to view their details!\n\n

{REFORM_BITHYNIA_II_TITLE}Bithynian Reforms II
{REFORM_BITHYNIA_II_BODY}Praise you, great lord of Bithynia, basileios of the Greeks of Asia. You rule a mighty realm, and the Gods favour you. Now, we follow your instructions in forming two new units for our army that are better equipped than what we have ever seen. The Epibatai will fight on board our newly formed fleet and will surely terrify our enemies. They are well armed, yet skilled with the sling, and can thus fight in every position and situation. The royal peltasts are even more impressive, a bulwark of your kingdom, heavily armoured and elected from the best of our warriors. With them in our ranks, we will surely become invincible! Make sure to check the recruitment scroll to view their details!\n\n

¬ ============================
¬ Syracuse
{REFORM_SYRACUSE_TITLE}Syracusan Reforms
{REFORM_SYRACUSE_BODY}Chaire, Basileios, ruler of Sikelia, first citizen of Syrakousai, the queen of all cities! You have brought wealth and happiness to your people, you have restored the temples and pacified the land. Now, the time has come to conquer beyond Sicily and retake what the mighty Dionysios once ruled: the ancient valleys and bountiful coasts of Italia. For this enterprise, we have reformed our cavalry to bear the big Thureos shield, and we have re-equipped some of our Thureophoroi foot soldiers with heavier armour. These new units will make our army even more powerful. May Apollo guide us to victory - Syrakousai forever! Make sure to check the recruitment scroll to view their details!\n\n

¬ ============================
¬ Miletus

{REFORM_MILETUS_TITLE}Milesian Reforms
{REFORM_MILETUS_BODY}Hail, great king! Over time, our soldiers have encountered and slain many foes. This has also resulted in adopting new military strategies and equipment, that are represented through a number of reformed units that have now become available for recruitment. Make sure to check the recruitment scroll to view their details!\n\n

¬ ============================
¬ Pentapolis

{REFORM_PENTAPOLIS_TITLE}Pentapolitan Reforms
{REFORM_PENTAPOLIS_BODY}Esteemed Council of the Pentapolis! Many battles have been fought and much blood has been shed. As with all groups of people that get together, there are always those who perform better than others. And like the Tomians are the best polis in the pentapolis, their Epilektoi have shown to be the very best of soldiers. It’s time to make them an official part of our army! Make sure to check the recruitment scroll to view their details!\n\n

¬ ============================
¬ Gortyn

{REFORM_GORTYN_TITLE}Gortynian Reforms
{REFORM_GORTYN_BODY}Aristocrats: Hear us, citizens of Gortyn! Our lands are prospering, and you have brought home many valuable goods. But wars never end, and we need more of you to participate! To achieve that, we have decided to hand out cheaper – <cough> I mean better – shields for all of you! The thureos will make you as ferocious as the Galatians who fought the Greeks on the mainland, we are sure of it! Now go, do your duty!\n\nDemos: You want even more of us to die, while you lie around and enjoy our loot? You will join us on the field or die right here on the spot!\n\nAristocrats, frightened: Of course we would like to help you in battle, but in contrast to you, we have no proper protection, besides what we wear on our bodies.\n\nDemos: Then take our aspides you want to replace and learn to ride with them!\n\nMake sure to check the recruitment scroll to view their details!\n\n

¬ ============================
¬ Knossos

{REFORM_KNOSSOS_TITLE}Knossian Reforms
{REFORM_KNOSSOS_BODY}Knossian aristocrat: My dearest erastai! I have decided to ride into battle!\n\nErastai: Incredible! You are so brave!\n\nKnossian aristocrat: Also, along with the newest developments on the mainland, I shall take an aspis with me into battle!\n\nErastai: That must be truly heavy! What a hero!\n\nKnossian Xystophoros: Only cowards hide behind their shields, when their armour isn’t strong, and their horse isn’t fast enough!\n\nXystophoros’ Erastai: Yes, tell him!\n\nKnossian Xystophoros: I don’t need a shield. All I need is my trusty xyston and the favour of the gods.\n\nXystophoros’ Erastai: You are the god’s and our favourite!\n\nMake sure to check the recruitment scroll to view their details!\n\n

¬ ============================
¬ Sica Cavalry

{REFORM_THRACIAN_SICA_CAVALRY_TITLE}Thracian Sica Cavalry Reforms
{REFORM_THRACIAN_SICA_CAVALRY_BODY}Hail, great king! Over time, our soldiers have encountered and slain many foes. This has also resulted in adopting new military strategies and equipment, that are represented through a number of reformed units that have now become available for recruitment. Make sure to check the recruitment scroll to view their details!\n\n

¬ ============================
¬ Kyzikan Aspidophoroi

{REFORM_KYZIKAN_ASPIDOPHOROI_TITLE}Kyzikan Aspidophoroi Reforms
{REFORM_KYZIKAN_ASPIDOPHOROI_BODY}Hail, great king! Over time, our soldiers have encountered and slain many foes. This has also resulted in adopting new military strategies and equipment, that are represented through a number of reformed units that have now become available for recruitment. Make sure to check the recruitment scroll to view their details!\n\n

¬ ============================
¬ Kabylean Reforms

{REFORM_THUREOPHOROI_TITLE}Kabylean Reforms
{REFORM_THUREOPHOROI_BODY}Hail, glorious king of Kabyle. Your wisdom is unparalleled! You have united the Greeks and the Thracians under your rule and your forces grow ever stronger. The long shields of the ferocious Celts, the thureoi, have been adopted by many peoples of Greece and Thrace, so why shouldn’t we as well? They are cheap and protect the body better than any other shield; an excellent choice for the increasing numbers of Greeks under our banners. Make sure to check the recruitment scroll to view their details!\n\n


¬ ============================
¬ Illyrian Epilektoi

{REFORM_ILLYRIAN_EPILEKTOI_TITLE}Illyrian Epilektoi Reform
{REFORM_ILLYRIAN_EPILEKTOI_BODY}Oh great king of Illyria! Thanks to your excellent leadership, your realm and army have considerably grown in size! Among our men are plenty of brave warriors who have shown the greatest courage and determination and would readily die for you in battle. It is time to separate the wheat from the chaff and pick these men out to serve in their own unit, which the Greeks call ‘epilektoi’. They shall move swiftly over the battlefield and strike fear into the hearts of your enemies!
Make sure to check the recruitment scroll to view the details!


¬ ============================
¬ Labeataean Reforms

{REFORM_LABEATAEAN_THUREOPHOROI_TITLE}Labeataean Thureophoroi Reform
{REFORM_LABEATAEAN_THUREOPHOROI_BODY}Ahoy, me fellow Labeatai! Many battles we have fought against our foreign neighbours and you have seen for yourself how fast and unwavering they were! Their secret must lie in their shields! I have seen it for meself! Flat and almost as large as a man - like a small raft - with which you could float over our great lake! We must take these shields for ourselves and show these suckers what real men can do with them! HA!
Make sure to check the recruitment scroll to view the details!


¬ ============================
¬ Illyrian Thureophoroi Cavalry Reforms

{REFORM_ILLYRIAN_THUREOPHOROI_CAV_TITLE}Illyrian Thureophoroi Cavalry Reform
{REFORM_ILLYRIAN_THUREOPHOROI_CAV_BODY}Hear me, king, you, who is blessed by the sun and the snake and the sea, lend your ear to a simple man, but a man of honour. For Illyrios is my witness that I fought bravely in many bloody battles against the greedy Celts and the arrogant Greeks and that I saved your nephew during the battle of the green cliffs. Though no one can match the extraordinary courage  of the Illyrians, we should be open to improving the equipment of our warriors. In many campaigns fought for you, my lord, and in my service as a mercenary for the proud Molossians and the mighty Macedonians, I have seen both Hellenes and Galatians use the big Thureos shield while riding their horses. Just image the terror we will strike into the hearts of our enemies if our mean can discharge their javelins from behind these large shields! Listen to me, and give our horsemen those shields, so they can lead you to victory!
Make sure to check the recruitment scroll to view the details!


¬ ============================
¬ Dardanian Pikemen

{REFORM_DARDANIAN_PIKEMEN_TITLE}Dardanian Pikemen Reform
{REFORM_DARDANIAN_PIKEMEN_BODY}DARDANIAN SOLDIERS! STAND AT ATTENTION! Hold you pike straight up! STRAIGHT UP I SAID! Keep a close eye on what the man in front of you does! NOW, MARCH! Good … and now … stop! STOP, I SAID, YOU BUFFOONS! Back into you positions! … Good. Now, resume marching! Aaaaand wheel to the right! … WHAT ARE YOU DOING! CAN’T YOU FOOLS TELL LEFT FROM RIGHT? We’ll repeat that until you’ve learned to properly march in formation and wheel the phalanx around! If we want to take on our damned Macedonian neighbours, we must meet them on equal ground! And from the start: MEN! READY YOUR PIKES! STAND AT ATTENTION! NOW MARCH!
Make sure to check the recruitment scroll to view the details!


¬ ============================
¬ Iapodian Swordsmen

{REFORM_IAPODIAN_SWORDMEN_TITLE}Iapodian Swordsmen Reform
{REFORM_IAPODIAN_SWORDMEN_BODY}Hail King! We’ve taken over the settlement and looked through their treasuries and armouries. These people have armours, like tunics that are made of iron rings. It is as sturdy as a thorax but still almost as flexible as a tunic! The making of this armour will likely take a while and be very costly, but it will protect our warriors a great deal! Only the best should wear it for now.
Make sure to check the recruitment scroll to view the details!


¬ ============================
¬ Dalmatian/Liburnian Thureophoroi

{REFORM_ILLYRIAN_THUREOPHOROI_TITLE}Illyrian Thureophoroi Reform
{REFORM_ILLYRIAN_THUREOPHOROI_BODY}Hail King! You have brought peace, stability, and wealth to our tribes and united them under your guidance. You have helped our settlements prosper and many powers now seek trade with us. The Greeks have sent us armour, money, and advisors all of which could make our warriors even more effective on the battlefield. Their cuirasses are made of linen and are a great addition to our bronze pectoral armour and our large thureos shields. We shall use that for our strongest soldiers and make us even more unstoppable!
Make sure to check the recruitment scroll to view the details!


¬ ============================
¬ Aspidophoroi 1

{REFORM_ASPIDOPHOROI_ONE_TITLE}Greek Reforms: Aspidophoroi
{REFORM_ASPIDOPHOROI_ONE_BODY}Chairete, noble citizens! We have received word that other Greek cities have started equipping some of their cavalrymen with shields…\n\nAssembly: COWARDS!!\n\nNow now, do not be so quick to judge. This new kind of cavalry has apparently proven to be quite effective for them. The enemies we face are not the same as those of our forefathers. We cannot afford to ignore such military developments, lest we fall behind and end up under some wanna-be-Alexander’s heel.\n\nAssembly: <murmuring>\n\nI say we institute this reform and make our own aspidophoroi. We need only to provide our existing cavalry with shields and appropriate armour if they do not already possess it. I assure you this will be quite the force. I’ve already made some preparations. Make sure to check the recruitment scroll to view their details!\n\n

¬ ============================
¬ Aspidophoroi 2

{REFORM_ASPIDOPHOROI_TWO_TITLE}Greek Reforms: Aspidophoroi
{REFORM_ASPIDOPHOROI_TWO_BODY}Chairete, noble citizens! We have received word that other Greek cities have started equipping some of their cavalrymen with shields…\n\nAssembly: COWARDS!!\n\nNow now, do not be so quick to judge. This new kind of cavalry has apparently proven to be quite effective for them. The enemies we face are not the same as those of our forefathers. We cannot afford to ignore such military developments, lest we fall behind and end up under some wanna-be-Alexander’s heel.\n\nAssembly: <murmuring>\n\nI say we institute this reform and make our own aspidophoroi. We need only to provide our existing cavalry with shields and appropriate armour if they do not already possess it. I assure you this will be quite the force. I’ve already made some preparations. Make sure to check the recruitment scroll to view their details!\n\n

¬ ============================
¬ Aspidophoroi 3

{REFORM_ASPIDOPHOROI_THREE_TITLE}Greek Reforms: Aspidophoroi
{REFORM_ASPIDOPHOROI_THREE_BODY}Chairete, noble citizens! We have received word that other Greek cities have started equipping some of their cavalrymen with shields…\n\nAssembly: COWARDS!!\n\nNow now, do not be so quick to judge. This new kind of cavalry has apparently proven to be quite effective for them. The enemies we face are not the same as those of our forefathers. We cannot afford to ignore such military developments, lest we fall behind and end up under some wanna-be-Alexander’s heel.\n\nAssembly: <murmuring>\n\nI say we institute this reform and make our own aspidophoroi. We need only to provide our existing cavalry with shields and appropriate armour if they do not already possess it. I assure you this will be quite the force. I’ve already made some preparations. Make sure to check the recruitment scroll to view their details!\n\n

¬ ============================
¬ Thureophoroi Cavalry

{REFORM_THUREOPHOROI_CAVALRY_TITLE}Greek Reforms: Thureophoroi Cavalry
{REFORM_THUREOPHOROI_CAVALRY_BODY}Chairete, noble citizens! I come to you with a proposal. Light missile cavalry has become increasingly popular amongst the Greeks, especially those adopting the Tarantine style of combat. However, I offer you an alternative. Greek states across the civilised world have begun equipping some of their light cavalry with the Celtic thureos shield, instead. This affords them additional protection as they pepper their foes with javelins or charge lighter troops. I say we adopt this new kind of cavalry! The initial investment will be small, yet I have no doubt it will prove to be a boon to our forces. Make sure to check the recruitment scroll to view their details!\n\n

¬ ============================
¬ Thorakitai

{REFORM_THORAKITAI_TITLE}Greek Reforms: Thorakitai
{REFORM_THORAKITAI_BODY}Chairete, noble Greeks! I speak to you today in the hope of instituting much-needed reforms in our military. In this age of barbarism and endless war, brave citizens wielding aspis and spear no longer suffice to stem the tide of ruin. Gauls threaten the Greek cities of Asia, Roman barbarians already rule our brothers in the West, and Hellas itself is under the heel of Makedonian kings. We could be next. If our fair city is to survive, we MUST adapt!\n\nAssembly: Yes yes, get on with it already! What do you suggest?\n\nI propose we raise the necessary funds and arm professional regiments of men in the style of the very barbarian brutes who threaten us.\n\nAssembly: <murmuring>\n\nWith a small investment, we could equip and train our men as thorakitai. Give our men thureos shields, swords, javelins, and sturdy armour, and I guarantee you we will be able to match any foe!\n\nAssembly: <Roars of agreement>\n\n

¬ ============================
¬ Cilician Alert

{CILICIAN_REBELLION_II_PLAY_AS_REBELS_MESSAGE}Cilicia for the Cilicians!
{CILICIAN_REBELLION_II_PLAY_AS_REBELS_MESSAGE_BODY}Cilicians are a strong people, and their skill as pirates is unmatched. Yet, their home remains under the thumb of the very powers they abuse. No more! It is time to see how well the men of Cilicia fight when they have a domain of their own to defend.\n\nHISTORICAL BACKGROUND\n\nCilicia in southeastern Anatolia, most famous for its pirates, was split into two regions. Kilikia Pedias to the east, with fertile plains and thus more cities, and Kilikia Traxeia to the west, a rough and mountainous land with a narrow coast (Strab. 14.5.1). It had been ruled by many different kingdoms before finally coming to the Romans around 102 BC (Brunson, Dictionary (1995), p. 90). While the plains were easy to administer, the hard-to-reach areas in Kilikia Traxeia were more of a challenge. The region was home to numerous pirate gangs, with their chief seat located at The Crags, until Pompey intervened in 67 BC (App. Mithr. 14.92, Plut. Pomp. 24). He made his ally, Tarkondimotos, king over the Cilicians. This practice of governing through clients would continue for over a century (Strab. 14.5.18). Augustus subsequently gave Kilikia Traxeia to Amyntas of Galatia and Archelaos of Kappadokia (Strab. 14.5.6, 54.9.1). Caligula would then give the region to Antiochos IV of Kommagene (Suet. Calig. 16.3). Yet, the Cilicians still had their wild spirit, and they continued to cause trouble, revolting at least twice under Tacitus and Vespasian before definitively being integrated around 109 AD (Tac. Ann 2.42; Braund, Friendly King (1984), p. 180, n. 81).

¬ ============================
¬ size1

{size1_enable}City State
{size1_enable_body}A flourishing city, ready to take the world.\n\nThe empire size is a balancing system to control the player's and the AI's tax income. Small factions receive tax bonuses, while big factions trade their income for law and happiness bonuses.\n\nEmpire size one: 1 city

{size1_disable}Empire Size 1
{size1_disable_body}We are no longer empire size one: 1 City

¬ ============================
¬ size2

{size2_enable}Emerging Power
{size2_enable_body}A fledgling kingdom or city-state, beginning to consolidate power, expanding its influence over neighbouring territories.\n\nThe empire size is a balancing system to control the player's and the AI's tax income. Small factions receive tax bonuses, while big factions trade their income for law and happiness bonuses.\n\nWe are now empire size two: to 2-5 cities

{size2_disable}Empire Size 2
{size2_disable_body}We are no longer empire size two: 2 to 5 cities

¬ ============================
¬ size3

{size3_enable}Minor Power
{size3_enable_body}Well consolidated kingdom or city state, respected and feared from its neighbours in the region.\n\nThe empire size is a balancing system to control the player's and the AI's tax income. Small factions receive tax bonuses, big factions trade their income for law and happiness bonuses.\n\nWe are now empire size three: 6 to 10 cities

{size3_disable}Empire Size 3
{size3_disable_body}We are no longer empire size three: 6 to 10 cities

¬ ============================
¬ size4

{size4_enable}Regional Power
{size4_enable_body}A significant player within its region, wielding considerable military, economic, and political influence with developing infrastructure, emerging bureaucracy, and increasing its centralization of power.\n\nThe empire size is a balancing system to control the player's and the AI's tax income. Small factions receive tax bonuses, while big factions trade their income for law and happiness bonuses.\n\nWe are now empire size four: 11 to 20 cities

{size4_disable}Empire Size 4
{size4_disable_body}We are no longer empire size four: 11 to 20 cities

¬ ============================
¬ size5

{size5_enable}Strong Regional Power
{size5_enable_body}A settled player within its region, wielding considerable military, economic, and political influence with infrastructure, efficient bureaucracy and centralizated power.\n\nThe empire size is a balancing system to control the player's and the AI's tax income. Small factions receive tax bonuses, while big factions trade their income for law and happiness bonuses.\n\nA We are now empire size five: 21 to 40 cities

{size5_disable}Empire Size 5
{size5_disable_body}We are no longer empire size five: 21 to 40 cities

¬ ============================
¬ size6

{size6_enable}Dominant Regional Power
{size6_enable_body}We have surpassed our neighbours in military might and territorial control, asserting dominance over a large portion of the region with a professional army, and established administrative institutions.\n\nThe empire size is a balancing system to control the player's and the AI's tax income. Small factions receive tax bonuses, while big factions trade their income for law and happiness bonuses.\n\nWe are now empire size six: 41 to 80 cities

{size6_disable}Empire Size 6
{size6_disable_body}We are no longer empire size six: 41 to 80 cities

¬ ============================
¬ size7

{size7_enable}Hegemonic Power
{size7_enable_body}We now exercise hegemony over the entire region, eclipsing all other powers and shaping regional politics and trade.\n\nThe empire size is a balancing system to control the player's and the AI's tax income. Small factions receive tax bonuses, while big factions trade their income for law and happiness bonuses.\n\nWe are now empire size seven: 81 to 160 cities

{size7_disable}Empire Size 7
{size7_disable_body}We are no longer empire size seven: 81 to 160 cities

¬ ============================
¬ size8

{size8_enable}Imperial Power
{size8_enable_body}We are now an expansive empire that extends its reach beyond its immediate region, subjugating distant lands and diverse cultures with strong administrative structures, and a formidable military apparatus.\n\nThe empire size is a balancing system to control the player's and the AI's tax income. Small factions receive tax bonuses, while big factions trade their income for law and happiness bonuses.\n\nWe are now empire size eight: 161 to 320 cities

{size8_disable}Empire Size 8
{size8_disable_body}We are no longer empire size eight: 161 to 320 cities

¬ ============================
¬ size9

{size9_enable}Imperial Hegemon
{size9_enable_body}An empire that dominates multiple regions, wielding unmatched military, economic, and cultural influence on a continental scale.\n\nThe empire size is a balancing system to control the player's and the AI's tax income. Small factions receive tax bonuses, while big factions trade their income for law and happiness bonuses.\n\nWe are now empire size nine: 321 to 640 cities

{size9_disable}Empire Size 9
{size9_disable_body}We are no longer empire size nine: 321 to 640 cities

¬ ============================
¬ size10

{size10_enable}Global Hegemon
{size10_enable_body}A superpower that reigns supreme on the world stage, exerting unparalleled influence across continents and oceans with unrivalled military supremacy, global trade dominance, cultural diffusion and assimilation.\n\nThe empire size is a balancing system to control the player's and the AI's tax income. Small factions receive tax bonuses, while big factions trade their income for law and happiness bonuses.\n\nWe are now empire size ten: 641 cities and higher

{size10_disable}Empire Size 10
{size10_disable_body}We are no longer empire size ten: 641 cities and higher
