¬ Localisation file for transition screen quotes
¬ Lines in brackets are not to be translated

{Quote_1}
If you have boats available, it is best to make a pursuit by sea and so keep the soldiers fresh; for thus you will outdistance the enemy and secure the other advantages you need, as long as your passage by sea is unobserved.
{Author_1}
Aineias the Tactician, How to Survive under Siege, 16.13

¬ for it is well known that a man who does not know the ground is not only unable to carry out his own plans, but finds it hard enough to retreat in safety if the defenders choose to attack him. Thus with no heart for anything and afraid to move, because they cannot foresee their opponents' movements, they are doomed to failure. For there will be as much difference between your position and theirs if they were fighting in the dark and you in broad daylight, supposing this could happen at once.
¬
{Quote_2}
For it is well known that a man who does not know the ground is not only unable to carry out his own plans, but finds it hard enough to retreat in safety if the defenders choose to attack him. ...
{Author_2}
Aineias the Tactician, How to Survive under Siege, 16.20

¬ During the fight you should encourage the men on the wall with tact and discrimination: give a word of praise to those who deserve it; make a special appeal to those who need it. Do not lose your temper with any of the rank and file: it will only dishearten them; if a reproof for negligence and insubordination is necessary,
¬
{Quote_3}
During the fight you should encourage the men on the wall with tact and discrimination: give a word of praise to those who deserve it; make a special appeal to those who need it. Do not lose your temper with any of the rank and file: it will only dishearten them; ...
{Author_3}
Aineias the Tactician, How to Survive under Siege, 38.4

¬  If the enemy attempt to set anything on fire with highly inflammable materials, you should use vinegar to put the fire out: this will make it hard to set alight again. Better still, smear it beforehand with birdlime: for this is fireproof.
¬
{Quote_4}
If the enemy attempt to set anything on fire ..., you should use vinegar to put the fire out: this will make it hard to set alight again. Better still, smear it beforehand with birdlime: for this is fireproof.
{Author_4}
Aineias the Tactician, How to Survive under Siege, 34.1

¬ Again, the men of Sinope, when at war with Datamas, were in a critical position and in want of men. They therefore disguised and armed the fittest of their women, so as to make them look as much as men as they could, gave them jars and similar brass utensils to represent armour and helmets, and marched them round the walls in full view of the enemy.
¬
{Quote_5}
Again, the men of Sinope ... were in a critical position and in want of men. They therefore disguised and armed the fittest of their women, ... gave them jars and similar brass utensils to represent armour and helmets, and marched them round the walls in full view of the enemy.
{Author_5}
Aineias the Tactician, How to Survive under Siege, 40.4

¬ Outposts, too, must be posted by day in front of the city, on high ground visible from as great a distance as possible: each group should consist of at least three men, specially chosen for their experience. Otherwise, you will have scouts who know no better, imagining dangers and reporting them by hand signal to the city, thus causing needless panics.
¬
{Quote_6}
Outposts, too, must be posted ...: each group should consist of at least three men, specially chosen for their experience. Otherwise, you will have scouts who know no better, imagining dangers and reporting them by hand signal to the city ...
{Author_6}
Aineias the Tactician, How to Survive under Siege, 6.1

¬ The men should be assembled at the gates as they come up, till a certain number, say one or two companies, has arrived; then, after they have been properly formed up and a capable leader placed in command, they should be sent on as fast as they can go without losing their formation.
¬
{Quote_7}
The men should be assembled at the gates as they come up, until a certain number ... has arrived; then, after they have been properly formed up and a capable leader placed in command, they should be sent on as fast as they can go without losing their formation.
{Author_7}
Aineias the Tactician, How to Survive under Siege, 15.3

¬  This will be when your force is in readiness at the place appointed and the enemy have dispersed in search of plunder: then is the time to attack, cutting off their lines of retreat with your cavalry and using your picked men for ambushes; the rest of the light troops should keep in touch with the enemy, while heavy infantry is brought up in column not far from the detachments sent in advance. Make your attack in a position where you need not fight if you do not want to, but where the advantage will be on your side if you choose to fight.
¬
{Quote_8}
... Make your attack in a position where you need not fight if you do not want to, but where the advantage will be on your side if you choose to fight.
{Author_8}
Aineias the Tactician, How to Survive under Siege, 16.7

¬ The passwords given should therefore be easy to remember, and as nearly related as possible to the business in hand: for instance, for a foray ‘Artemis the Huntress’; for secret exploits ‘Hermes the cunning’; in case of an assault ‘Herakles’; for open attacks ‘Sun’ and ‘Moon’; and so on as far as possible, using words that will be intelligible to all.
¬
{Quote_9}
The passwords given should therefore be easy to remember, and as nearly related as possible to the business in hand: for instance, for a foray 'Artemis the Huntress'; for secret exploits 'Hermes the cunning'; in case of an assault 'Herakles'; ...
{Author_9}
Aineias the Tactician, How to Survive under Siege, 24.14-15

¬ In the next place, the sentinels at the gates must be men specially selected for intelligence and presence of mind, who will not fail to look with suspicion upon everything brought into the town; they should also be well-to-do men, and bound by ties of family – that is to say, a wife and children – to be loyal to their city, not men whom poverty, difficulty in meeting their commitments or other troubles might make ready supporters or actual instigators of any mutinous design.
¬
{Quote_10}
In the next place, the sentinels at the gates must be men specially selected ..., who will not fail to look with suspicion upon everything brought into the town; they should also be well-to-do men, and bound by ties of family ... to be loyal to their city, ...
{Author_10}
Aineias the Tactician, How to Survive under Siege, 5.1

¬ Particulars have already been given of the way to deal with political malcontents. It is very important that unanimity (homonoia) among the citizens in general should be secured for the time being by various conciliatory measures, such as the relief of debtors by the reduction or abolition of interest: in a very dangerous crisis even the capital sum owed may be partly, or, of necessary, wholly cancelled, as insolvent debtors are very dangerous adversaries to have sitting by, watching for their opportunity. Those in want of the necessaries of life should be amply provided for.
¬
{Quote_11}
... It is very important that unanimity among the citizens in general should be secured ... by various conciliatory measures, such as the relief of debtors ...: in a very dangerous crisis even the capital sum owed may be partly, or, if necessary, wholly cancelled, ...
{Author_11}
Aineias the Tactician, How to Survive under Siege, 14.1

¬ For you must know that if your adversaries are men of judgement and skill, they will at first keep their best troops in hand when in the enemy's country; for they will expect an attack and be prepared to repulse it. Some of them in small detachments will be going about the country plundering, while others will probably be in ambush, ready for any undisciplined attempts of reprisal on your part.
¬
{Quote_12}
For you must know that if your adversaries are men of judgement and skill, they will at first keep their best troops in hand when in the enemy's country; for they will expect an attack and be prepared to repulse it. ...
{Author_12}
Aineias the Tactician, How to Survive under Siege, 16.4

¬ In the first place, it is undesirable to attempt immediate reprisals ‹at dawn›; for you must remember that before daybreak your men will be unprepared and in great disorder, some eager to save their own property on the farms without loss of time, others afraid to advance boldly to meet the danger, as is natural in the case of sudden alarm, others again caught entirely unprepared.
¬
{Quote_13}
... it is undesirable to attempt immediate reprisals; for ... before daybreak your men will be unprepared and in great disorder, some eager to save their own property ..., others afraid to advance boldly to meet the danger, ... others again caught entirely unprepared.
{Author_13}
Aineias the Tactician, How to Survive under Siege, 16.2

¬ If your country is not easy to invade, and the ways leading into it a few and narrow, these, as I have said, should be occupied in advance: then, with your detachments posted at the several entrances, you should resist the attack of the force moving on the city; your dispositions should be made in advance, and the fortunes of each detachment made known to the others by fire signals, to enable them to reinforce each other in case of need.
¬
{Quote_14}
If your country is not easy to invade, and the ways leading into it a few and narrow, these, as I have said, should be occupied in advance, ... and the fortunes of each detachment made known to the others by fire signals, to enable them to reinforce each other in case of need.
{Author_14}
Aineias the Tactician, How to Survive under Siege, 16.16

¬ Your familiarity with the ground must always be used to advantage in delivering attacks; you will gain a great deal by previous knowledge of the country, and by being able to entice the enemy into whatever sort of country suits you best, where you know your ground and are at liberty to act on the defensive, to pursue, retreat, or withdraw either secretly or openly to the city (especially as you will also know where to find your supplies); while the enemy, strangers in an unfamiliar country, can derive from it none of these advantages:
¬
{Quote_15}
Your familiarity with the ground must always be used to advantage in delivering attacks; you will gain a great deal by previous knowledge of the country, and by being able to entice the enemy into whatever sort of country suits you best, ...
{Author_15}
Aineias the Tactician, How to Survive under Siege, 16.19

¬ In the next place, the sentinels at the gates must be men specially selected for intelligence and presence of mind, who will not fail to look with suspicion upon everything brought into the town; they should also be well-to-do men, and bound by ties of family – that is to say, a wife and children – to be loyal to their city, not men whom poverty, difficulty in meeting their commitments or other troubles might make ready supporters or actual instigators of any mutinous design. [2] Leucon, tyrant of Bosporus, used to discharge even members of his bodyguard who got into debt through gambling or any kind of loose living.
¬
{Quote_16}
... difficulty in meeting their commitments or other troubles might make ready supporters or actual instigators of any mutinous design. Leukon, tyrant of Bosporos, used to discharge even members of his bodyguard who got into debt through gambling or any kind of loose living.
{Author_16}
Aineias the Tactician, How to Survive under Siege, 5.1-2

¬ The organization of troops should be made with reference to the size of the city, the situation of its buildings, the posting of guards and rounds, and any other service for which troops are required in the city: all these points must be borne in mind in making the allotment.
¬
{Quote_17}
The organization of troops should be made with reference to the size of the city, the situation of its buildings, the posting of guards and rounds, and any other service for which troops are required in the city: all these points must be borne in mind in making the allotment.
{Author_17}
Aineias the Tactician, How to Survive under Siege, 1.1

¬ At Apollonia on the Pontos, where one of the above ruses had been practiced with success, the gates were so constructed as to be shut to the sound of a big hammer, which made a tremendous noise, so that almost the whole city could hear when the gates were being shut or opened, the fastenings being very heavy and plated with iron.
¬
{Quote_18}
At Apollonia on the Pontos, where one of the [bolt-tampering] ruses had been practiced with success, the gates were so constructed as to be shut to the sound of a big hammer, ... so that almost the whole city could hear when the gates were being shut or opened, ...
{Author_18}
Aineias the Tactician, How to Survive under Siege, 20.4

¬ At times when assaults are being made on the wall either by machines or by actual storming parties, the fighting force of the city should be divided into three parts, so that there may always be one part in action, another off duty, and the third preparing for action: thus the troops will always be fresh.
¬
{Quote_19}
At times when assaults are being made on the wall either by machines or by actual storming parties, the fighting force of the city should be divided into three parts, so that there may always be one part in action, another off duty, and the third preparing for action ...
{Author_19}
Aineias the Tactician, How to Survive under Siege, 38.1

¬ It might happen, however, that an old man had a young wife; and he observed that old men keep a very jealous watch over their young wives. To meet these cases he instituted an entirely different system by requiring the elderly husband to introduce into his house some man whose physical and moral qualities he admired, in order to beget children.
¬
{Quote_20}
... [Lykourgos] observed that old men keep a very jealous watch over their young wives. ... he instituted an entirely different system by requiring the elderly husband to introduce into his house some man whose physical and moral qualities he admired, in order to beget children.
{Author_20}
Xenophon, Polity of the Lakedaimonians, 1.7

¬ On the other hand, in case a man did not want to cohabit with his wife and nevertheless desired children of whom he could be proud, he made it lawful for him to choose a woman who was the mother of a fine family and of high birth, and if he obtained her husband's consent, to make her the mother of his children.
¬
{Quote_21}
... in case a man did not want to cohabit with his wife and nevertheless desired children of whom he could be proud, [Lykourgos] made it lawful for him to choose a woman ... of high birth, and if he obtained her husband's consent, to make her the mother of his children.
{Author_21}
Xenophon, Polity of the Lakedaimonians, 1.8

¬ Having made sure that the horses are in good condition, the next business is to train the men. First they must learn to mount from the spring,2 since many before now have owed their lives to that. Secondly, they must practise riding over all sorts of ground, since any kind of country may become the area of war. [6] As soon as they have acquired a firm seat, your next task is to take steps that as many as possible shall be able to throw the javelin when mounted3 and shall become efficient in all the details of horsemanship.
¬
{Quote_22}
... First [the cavalrymen] must learn to mount from a jump, ... . Secondly, they must practise riding over all sorts of ground, ... . As soon as they have acquired a firm seat, ... take steps that as many as possible shall be able to throw the javelin when mounted ...
{Author_22}
Xenophon, On the Cavalry Commander, 1.5-6

¬ When your men are well trained in all these points, they must, of course, understand some plan of formation, that in which they will show to greatest advantage in the sacred processions and at manoeuvres, fight, if need be, with the greatest courage, and move along roads and cross rivers with perfect ease in unbroken order.
¬
{Quote_23}
When your men are well trained ..., they must, of course, understand some plan of formation, that in which they will show to greatest advantage in the sacred processions and at manoeuvres, ... and move along roads and cross rivers with perfect ease in unbroken order.
{Author_23}
Xenophon, On the Cavalry Commander, 2.1

¬ You must be very careful to appoint a competent man as leader in the rear. For if he is a good man, his cheers will always hearten the ranks in front of him in case it becomes necessary to charge; or, should the moment come to retreat, his prudent leadership will, in all probability, do much for the safety of his regiment.
¬
{Quote_24}
You must be very careful to appoint a competent man as leader in the rear. For ... his cheers will always hearten the ranks in front of him ... or, should the moment come to retreat, his prudent leadership will ... do much for the safety of his fellow men.
{Author_24}
Xenophon, On the Cavalry Commander, 2.5

¬ First, he must sacrifice to propitiate the gods on behalf of the cavalry; secondly, he must make the processions during the festivals worth seeing; further, he must conduct all the other obligatory displays before the people with as much splendour as possible, that is to say, the reviews in the Academy, in the Lyceum, at Phalerum, and in the Hippodrome.
¬
{Quote_25}
First, [the cavalry commander] must sacrifice to propitiate the gods on behalf of the cavalry; secondly, he must make the processions during the festivals worth seeing; further, he must conduct all ... obligatory displays before the people with as much splendour as possible ...
{Author_25}
Xenophon, On the Cavalry Commander, 3.1

¬ Every horseman should know at what distance a horse can overtake a man on foot, and how much start a slow horse needs to escape from a fast one. A cavalry commander should also be able to judge of the ground where infantry has an advantage over cavalry and where cavalry has an advantage over infantry.
¬
{Quote_26}
... A cavalry commander should also be able to judge the ground where infantry has an advantage over cavalry and where cavalry has an advantage over infantry.
{Author_26}
Xenophon, On the Cavalry Commander, 5.1

¬ Another duty of a cavalry commander is to demonstrate to the city the weakness of cavalry destitute of infantry as compared with cavalry that has infantry attached to it. Further, having got his infantry, a cavalry commander should make use of it. A mounted man being much higher than a man on foot, infantry may be hidden away not only among the cavalry but in the rear as well.
¬
{Quote_27}
... Further, having got his infantry, a cavalry commander should make use of it. A mounted man being much higher than a man on foot, infantry may be hidden away not only among the cavalry but in the rear as well.
{Author_27}
Xenophon, On the Cavalry Commander, 5.13

¬ He must therefore practise every detail of horsemanship—mounting and the rest,—that they may see their commander able to take a ditch without a spill, clear a wall, leap down from a bank and throw a javelin skilfully. For all these feats are so many stepping stones to their respect.
¬
{Quote_28}
[The cavalry commander] must therefore practise every detail of horsemanship ... that they may see their commander able to take a ditch without a spill, clear a wall, leap down from a bank and throw a javelin skilfully. ...
{Author_28}
Xenophon, On the Cavalry Commander, 6.5

¬ It happens that, the greater is the number of soldiers, the more they are apt to blunder. Either they scatter deliberately in search of provisions, or they are so careless of order on the march that some get too far ahead, while others lag too far behind. [10] So he must not let such blunders go unpunished, or the whole country will be occupied; only he must take good care to retire the moment he has struck, without giving time for the main supports to arrive on the scene.
¬
{Quote_29}
It happens that, the greater is the number of soldiers, the more they are apt to blunder. ... So [the cavalry commander] must not let such blunders go unpunished, or the whole country will be occupied; ...
{Author_29}
Xenophon, On the Cavalry Commander, 7.9-10

¬ Besides, patrols are easily deceived, for they pursue a handful of men at sight, believing that to be their special duty. You must see, however, that your line of retreat does not lead you straight into the enemy's supports.
¬
{Quote_30}
Besides, patrols are easily deceived, for they pursue a handful of men at sight, believing that to be their special duty. You must see, however, that your line of retreat does not lead you straight into the enemy's supports.
{Author_30}
Xenophon, On the Cavalry Commander, 7.15

¬ On the contrary, those that are taught and accustomed to jump ditches, leap walls, spring up banks, leap down from heights without a spill, and gallop down steep places, will be as superior to the men and horses that lack this training as birds to beasts. Moreover, those that have their feet well hardened will differ on rough ground from the tender-footed as widely as the sound from the lame. And those that are familiar with the locality, compared with those to whom it is unfamiliar, will differ in the advance and retreat as much as men with eyes differ from the blind.
¬
{Quote_31}
... men in training for gymnastic contests face troubles far more numerous and exacting than the most strenuous votaries of horsemanship. For most gymnastic exercises are carried out with sweat and drudgery, but nearly all equestrian exercises are pleasant work. ...
{Author_31}
Xenophon, On the Cavalry Commander, 8.5-6

¬ It should be noticed that a long apprenticeship to toil enables sea-pirates to live at the expense of much stronger folk. On land, too, pillage, though not for those who reap what they have sown, is the natural resource of men who are deprived of food. For either men must work or they must eat the fruits of other men's labour: else it is a problem how to live and to obtain peace.
¬
{Quote_32}
It should be noticed that a long apprenticeship to toil enables sea-pirates to live at the expense of much stronger folk. On land, too, pillage ... is the natural resource of men who are deprived of food.
{Author_32}
Xenophon, On the Cavalry Commander, 8.8

¬ If you charge a superior force, you must remember never to leave behind you ground difficult for horses. For a fall in retreat and a fall in pursuit are very different things.
¬
{Quote_33}
If you charge a superior force, you must remember never to leave behind you ground difficult for horses. For a fall in retreat and a fall in pursuit are very different things.
{Author_33}
Xenophon, On the Cavalry Commander, 8.9

¬ The right procedure, in my opinion, is just the opposite: when the commander expects to win, he should not hesitate to use the whole of his strength: for an overwhelming victory never yet was followed by remorse.
¬
{Quote_34}
... when the commander expects to win, he should not hesitate to use the whole of his strength: for an overwhelming victory never yet was followed by remorse.
{Author_34}
Xenophon, On the Cavalry Commander, 8.11

¬ Both divisions should have an infantry contingent; and if the infantry, hidden away behind the cavalry, came out suddenly and went for the enemy, I think they would prove an important factor in making the victory more decisive; for I have noticed that a surprise cheers men up if it is pleasant, but stuns them if it is alarming.
¬
{Quote_35}
Both divisions [of cavalry] should have an infantry contingent; and if the infantry, hidden away behind the cavalry, came out suddenly and went for the enemy, I think they would prove an important factor in making the victory more decisive; ...
{Author_35}
Xenophon, On the Cavalry Commander, 8.19

¬ For the commander must be capable both by his words and action of making the men under him realize that it is good to obey, to back up their leader, and to charge home; of firing them with a desire to win commendation; and of enabling them to carry out their intentions with persistence.
¬
{Quote_36}
For the commander must be capable ... of making the men under him realize that it is good to obey, to back up their leader, and to charge home; of firing them with a desire to win commendation; and of enabling them to carry out their intentions with persistence.
{Author_36}
Xenophon, On the Cavalry Commander, 8.22

¬ Lions, leopards, lynxes, panthers, bears and all similar wild beasts are captured in foreign countries, about Mt. Pangaeus and Cittus beyond Macedonia, on Mysian Olympus and Pindus, on Nysa beyond Syria, and in other mountain ranges capable of supporting such animals.
¬
{Quote_37}
Lions, leopards, lynxes, panthers, bears and all similar wild beasts are captured in foreign countries, about Mount Pangaios and Kittos beyond Makedonia, on Mysian Olympos and Pindos, on Nysa beyond Syria, and in other mountain ranges capable of supporting such animals.
{Author_37}
Xenophon, On Hunting, 11.1

¬ The divisions remaining at home, in their turn, pass their time shooting with the bow and hurling the spear and practising all the other arts that they learned when they were boys, and they continually engage in contests of this kind with one another.
¬
{Quote_38}
The divisions [of Persian youths] remaining at home, ... pass their time shooting with the bow and hurling the spear and practising all the other arts that they learned when they were boys, and they continually engage in contests of this kind with one another.
{Author_38}
Xenophon, The Education of Kyros, 1.2.12

¬ This is the attitude in which artists represent the horses on which gods and heroes ride, and men who manage such horses gracefully have a magnificent appearance. [9] Indeed a prancing horse is a thing so graceful, terrible and astonishing that it rivets the gaze of all beholders, young and old alike. At all events no one leaves him or is tired of gazing at him so long as he shows off his brilliance.
¬
{Quote_39}
This [prancing] is the attitude in which artists represent the horses on which gods and heroes ride ... Indeed a prancing horse is a thing so graceful, terrible and astonishing that it rivets the gaze of all beholders, young and old alike. ...
{Author_39}
Xenophon, On Horsemanship, 11.8

¬ We recommend throwing the javelin at the longest range possible. For this gives a man more time to turn his horse and to grasp the other javelin. We will also state in a few words the most effective way of throwing the javelin. If a man, in the act of advancing his left side, drawing back his right, and rising from his thighs, discharges the javelin with its point a little upwards, he will give his weapon the strongest impetus and the furthest carrying power; it will be most likely to hit the mark, however, if at the moment of discharge the point is always set on it.
¬
{Quote_40}
We recommend throwing the javelin at the longest range possible. For this gives a man more time to turn his horse and to grasp the other javelin. ...
{Author_40}
Xenophon, On Horsemanship, 12.13

¬ But the Persians more than all men welcome foreign customs. They wear the Median dress, thinking it more beautiful than their own, and the Egyptian cuirass in war. Their luxurious practices are of all kinds, and all borrowed: the Greeks taught them pederasty. Every Persian marries many lawful wives, and keeps still more concubines.
¬
{Quote_41}
But the Persians more than all men welcome foreign customs. They wear the Median dress, thinking it more beautiful than their own, and the Egyptian cuirass in war. Their luxurious practices are of all kinds, and all borrowed: the Greeks taught them pederasty. ...
{Author_41}
Herodotos, Histories, 1.135.1

¬ They educate their boys from five to twenty years old, and teach them only three things: riding and archery and honesty. A boy is not seen by his father before he is five years old, but lives with the women: the point of this is that, if the boy should die in the interval of his rearing, the father would suffer no grief.
¬
{Quote_42}
[The Persians] educate their boys from five to twenty years old, and teach them only three things: riding and archery and honesty.
{Author_42}
Herodotos, Histories, 1.136.2

¬ Now really I do not think that I should be ashamed to write even the name of this dog; that it may be left to posterity, that Xenophon the Athenian had a greyhound called Horme, of the greatest speed and intelligence and altogether supremely excellent.
¬
{Quote_43}
Now really I do not think that I should be ashamed to write even the name of this dog; that it may be left to posterity, that [I] had a greyhound called Horme, of the greatest speed and intelligence and altogether supremely excellent.
{Author_43}
Arrianos, On Hunting, 5.6

¬ But while I am at home she remains within, by my side, accompanies me on going abroad, follows me to the gymnasium, and, while I am taking exercise, sits down by me. On my return she runs in front of me me, often looking back to see whether I had turned anywhere out of the road; and as soon as she catches sight of me, showing symptoms of joy, trots on again in front of me.
¬
{Quote_44}
On my return [my dog] runs in front of me, often looking back to see whether I had turned anywhere out of the road, and as soon as she catches sight of me, showing symptoms of joy, trots on again in front of me.
{Author_44}
Arrianos, On Hunting, 5.3

¬ She is, moreover (for while I am writing, she is yet alive), most gentle and kindly-affectioned, and never before had any dog such regard for myself nor my friend (and fellow-sportsman) Megillus.
¬
{Quote_45}
[My dog] is, moreover (for while I am writing, she is yet alive), most gentle and kindly-affectioned, and never before had any dog such regard for myself nor my friend (and fellow-sportsman) Megillus.
{Author_45}
Arrianos, On Hunting, 5.2

¬ If I am going out on any government business, she remains with my friend, and does exactly the same towards him. She is the constant companion of whichever may be sick, and if she has not seen either of us for only a short time, she jumps up repeatedly by way of salutation, and barks with joy as a greeting to us. At meals she pats us first with one foot and then with the other, to put us in mind that she is to have her share of food. She has also many tones of speech than I ever knew in any other dog—pointing out, in her own language, whatever she wants.
¬
{Quote_46}
... [My dog] is the constant companion of whichever may be sick, and if she has not seen either of us for only a short time, she jumps up repeatedly by way of salutation, and barks with joy as a greeting to us. ...
{Author_46}
Arrianos, On Hunting, 5.4

¬ On similar occasions men in want of shields, and unable to provide them in any other way or to convey arms into the city, had recourse to importing osiers and with them workers in osier, who plaited other articles in the daytime, [12] but at nights worked wicker armour, consisting of helmets and shields, to the rims of which they fixed leather and wood. Moreover, you should keep a sharp look-out on boats, both large and small, which take up moorings nearby, either by day or at night: the harbour officials and dockyard superintendents should go on board and inspect the cargoes in person, bearing in mind that the Sikyonians for instance suffered a great disaster from neglect of these precautions.
¬
{Quote_47}
On similar occasions men in want of shields, ... had recourse to importing osiers and with them workers in osier, who ... at nights worked wicker armour, consisting of helmets and shields, to the rims of which they fixed leather and wood.
{Author_47}
Aineias the Tactician, 29.11-12

¬ We want to explain also how a man who is to face danger on horseback should be armed. We say, then, that in the first place his breastplate must be made to fit his body. For the wellfitting breastplate is supported by the whole body, whereas one that is too loose is supported by the shoulders only, and one that is too tight is rather an encumbrance than a defence.
¬
{Quote_48}
We want to explain also how a man who is to face danger on horseback should be armed. We say, then, that in the first place his breastplate must be made to fit his body. For the wellfitting breastplate is supported by the whole body, ...
{Author_48}
Xenophon, On Horsemanship, 12.1

¬ For the helmet we consider the Boiotian pattern the most satisfactory: for this, again, affords the best protection to all the parts that project above the breastplate without obstructing the sight. As for the pattern of the breastplate, it should be so shaped as not to prevent the wearer from sitting down or stooping.
¬
{Quote_49}
For the helmet we consider the Boiotian pattern the most satisfactory: for this, again, affords the best protection to all the parts that project above the breastplate without obstructing the sight.
{Author_49}
Xenophon, On Horsemanship, 12.3

¬ The quilting of the cloth should be such as to give the rider a safer seat and not to gall the horse's back. Thus horse and man alike will be armed in most parts. [10] But the rider's shins and feet will of course be outside the thigh-pieces. These too can be guarded if boots made of shoe-leather are worn: there will thus be armour for the shins and covering for the feet at the same time.
¬
{Quote_50}
... thus horse and man alike will be armed in most parts. But the rider's shins and feet will of course be outside the thigh-pieces. These too can be guarded if boots made of shoe-leather are worn ...
{Author_50}
Xenophon, On Horsemanship, 12.9-11

¬ And as a wound in the left hand disables the rider, we also recommend the piece of armour invented for it called the 'cheires' (hand). For it protects the shoulder, the arm, the elbow, and the fingers that hold the reins; it will also extend and fold up; and in addition it covers the gap left by the breastplate under the armpit.
¬
{Quote_51}
... we also recommend the piece of armour invented for it called the 'cheires' (hand). For it protects the shoulder, the arm, the elbow, and the fingers that hold the reins; ... and in addition it covers the gap left by the breastplate under the armpit.
{Author_51}
Xenophon, On Horsemanship, 12.5

¬ Since the rider is seriously imperilled in the event of his horse being wounded, the horse also should be armed, having head, chest, and thigh pieces: the last also serve to cover the rider's thighs. But above all the horse's belly must be protected; for this, which is the most vital part, is also the weakest. It is possible to make the cloth serve partly as a protection to it.
¬
{Quote_52}
Since the rider is seriously imperilled in the event of his horse being wounded, the horse also should be armed, having head, chest, and thigh pieces: the last also serve to cover the rider's thighs. But above all the horse's belly must be protected ...
{Author_52}
Xenophon, On Horsemanship, 12.8

¬ For most of the soldiers had sailed away from Greece to undertake this service for pay, not because their means were scanty, but because they knew by report of the noble character of Cyrus; some brought other men with them, some had even spent money of their own on the enterprise, while still another class had abandoned fathers and mothers, or had left children behind with the idea of getting money to bring back to them, all because they heard that the other people who served with Cyrus enjoyed abundant good fortune. Being men of this sort, therefore, they longed to return in safety to Greece.
¬
{Quote_53}
For most of the soldiers had sailed away from Greece to undertake this service for pay ... [some] had abandoned fathers and mothers, or had left children behind with the idea of getting money to bring back to them, ... therefore, they longed to return in safety to Greece.
{Author_53}
Xenophon, Anabasis 6.4.8

¬ In the first place, as is reasonable, I shall begin my speech from my father Philip. For he found you vagabonds and destitute of means, most of you clad in hides, feeding a few sheep up the mountain sides, for the protection of which you had to fight with small success against Illyrians, Triballians, and the border Thracians. Instead of the hides he gave you cloaks to wear, and from the mountains he led you down into the plains, and made you capable of fighting the neighbouring barbarians, so that you were no longer compelled to preserve yourselves by trusting rather to the inaccessible strongholds than to your own valour.
¬
{Quote_54}
'... I shall begin my speech from my father Philip. For he found you ... fighting with small success against Illyrians, Triballians, and the border Thrakians. Instead of the hides he gave you cloaks to wear, and from the mountains he led you down into the plains, ...'
{Author_54}
A speech of Megas Alexandros at Opis as quoted by Arrianos, Anabasis of Alexandros, 7.9.2

¬ And upon hearing this Cyrus said, “Well, I accept it, and so let it be.” After he had said these words he rode back to his own position. At length the opposing lines were not three or four stadia apart, and then the Greeks struck up the paean and began to advance against the enemy. [18] And when, as they proceeded, a part of the phalanx billowed out, those who were thus left behind began to run; at the same moment they all set up the sort of war-cry which they raise to Enyalius, and all alike began running. It is also reported that some of them clashed their shields against their spears, thereby frightening the enemy's horses.
¬
{Quote_55}
... and then the Hellenes struck up the paean and began to advance against the enemy. And when, as they proceeded, a part of the phalanx billowed out, ... [and] at the same moment they all set up the sort of war-cry which they raise to Enyalios, and all alike began running. ...
{Author_55}
Xenophon, Anabasis, 1.8.17-18

¬ Nevertheless, I must say what I believe; for I am acquainted with both the country of the Paphlagonians and their power. Their country possesses these two things: the fairest plains and the loftiest mountains.
¬
{Quote_56}
Nevertheless, I must say what I believe; for I am acquainted with both the country of the Paphlagonians and their power. Their country possesses these two things: the fairest plains and the loftiest mountains.
{Author_56}
Xenophon, Anabasis, 5.6.6

¬ After they had made libations and sung the paean, two Thracians rose up first and began a dance in full armour to the music of an Aulos, leaping high and lightly and using their Machairai; finally, one struck the other, as everybody thought, and the second man fell, in a rather skilful way.
¬
{Quote_57}
After they had made libations and sung the paean, two Thracians rose up first and began a dance in full armour to the music of an Aulos, leaping high and lightly and using their Machairai; finally, one struck the other, ... and the second man fell, in a rather skilful way.
{Author_57}
Xenophon, Anabasis, 6.1.5

¬ After this a Mysian came in carrying a Pelte in each hand, and at one moment in his dance he would go through a pantomime as though two men were arrayed against him, again he would use his shields as though against one antagonist, and again he would whirl and throw somersaults while holding the shields in his hands, so that the spectacle was a fine one.
¬
{Quote_58}
After this a Mysian came in carrying a Pelte in each hand, and at one moment in his dance he would go through a pantomime as though two men were arrayed against him, ... and again he would whirl and throw somersaults while holding the shields in his hands, ...
{Author_58}
Xenophon, Anabasis, 6.1.9

¬ Thereupon the Mysian, seeing how astounded they were, persuaded one of the Arkadians who had a dancing girl to let him bring her in, after dressing her up in the finest way he could and giving her a Pelte. [13] And she danced the Pyrrhic with grace. Then there was great applause, and the Paphlagonians asked whether women also fought by their side.
¬
{Quote_59}
Thereupon the Mysian, ... persuaded one of the Arkadians who had a dancing girl to let him bring her in, after dressing her up in the finest way he could and giving her a Pelte. And she danced the Pyrrhic with grace. Then there was great applause, ...
{Author_59}
Xenophon, Anabasis, 6.1.12-13

¬ Lastly, he danced the Persian dance, clashing his shields together and crouching down and then rising up again; and all this he did, keeping time to the music of the Aulos.
¬
{Quote_60}
Lastly, [the Mysian] danced the Persian dance, clashing his shields together and crouching down and then rising up again; and all this he did, keeping time to the music of the Aulos.
{Author_60}
Xenophon, Anabasis, 6.1.10

¬ After him the Mantineians and some of the other Arkadians arose, arrayed in the finest arms and accoutrements they could command, and marched in time to the accompaniment of an Aulos playing the martial rhythm and sang the paean and danced, just as the Arcadians do in their festal processions in honour of the gods. And the Paphlagonians, as they looked on, thought it most strange that all the dances were under arms.
¬
{Quote_61}
After him the Mantineians and some of the other Arkadians arose, arrayed in the finest arms and accoutrements they could command, and marched in time to the accompaniment of an Aulos playing the martial rhythm and sang the paean and danced, ...
{Author_61}
Xenophon, Anabasis, 6.1.11

¬ After this some Ainianes and Magnetes arose and danced under arms the so-called 'Karpaia'. [8] The manner of the dance was this: a man is sowing and driving a yoke of oxen, his arms laid at one side, and he turns about frequently as one in fear; a robber approaches; as soon as the sower sees him coming, he snatches up his arms, goes to meet him, and fights with him to save his oxen. The two men do all this in rhythm to the music of the Aulos. Finally, the robber binds the man and drives off the oxen; or sometimes the master of the oxen binds the robber, and then he yokes him alongside the oxen, his hands tied behind him, and drives off.
¬
{Quote_62}
After this some Ainianes and Magnetes arose and danced under arms the so-called 'Karpaia'. The manner of the dance was this: a man is sowing and driving a yoke of oxen, ... [when] a robber approaches; ... [the sower] goes to meet him, and fights with him to save his oxen. ...
{Author_62}
Xenophon, Anabasis, 6.1.7-8

¬ As bowmen they were most excellent; they had bows nearly three cubits long and their arrows were more than two cubits, and when they shot, they would draw their strings by pressing with the left foot against the lower end of the bow, and their arrows would go straight through shields and breastplates. Whenever they got hold of them, the Hellenes would use these arrows as javelins, fitting them with thongs. In these regions the Kretans made themselves exceedingly useful. They were commanded by a Kretan named Stratokles.
¬
{Quote_63}
... [The Kardouchoi] had bows nearly three cubits long and their arrows were more than two cubits, ... they would draw their strings by pressing with the left foot against the lower end of the bow, and their arrows would go straight through shields and breastplates. ...
{Author_63}
Xenophon, Anabasis, 4.2.28

¬ When Mithridates heard this he went out to reason with them. A part of his own guard then ran to join the deserters, but the latter refused to admit them unless they would do some irreparable deed as a proof of their fidelity, pointing at the same time to Mithridates. So they hastened to kill his horse, for he himself had fled, and at the same time saluted Pharnaces as king, as though the rebels were already victorious, and one of them brought a broad papyrus leaf from a temple and crowned him with it in place of a diadem. The king saw these things from a high portico, and he sent messenger after messenger to Pharnaces asking permission to fly in safety. When none of his messengers returned, fearing lest he should be delivered up to the Romans, he praised the body-guards and friends who had been faithful to him and sent them to the new king, but the army killed some of them under a misapprehension as they were approaching. Mithridates then took out some poison that he always carried next to his sword, and mixed it. There two of his daughters, who were still girls growing up together, named Mithridatis and Nyssa, who had been betrothed to the kings of Egypt and of Cyprus, asked him to let them have some of the poison first, and insisted strenuously and prevented him from drinking it until they had taken some and swallowed it. The drug took effect on them at once; but upon Mithridates, although he walked around rapidly to hasten its action, it had no effect, because he had accustomed himself to other drugs by continually trying them as a means of protection against poisoners. These are still called the Mithridatic drugs. Seeing a certain Bituitus there, an officer of the Gauls, he said to him, 'I have profited much from your right arm against my enemies. I shall profit from it most of all if you will kill me, and save from the danger of being led in a Roman triumph one who has been an autocrat so many years, and the ruler of so great a kingdom, but who is now unable to die by poison because, like a fool, he has fortified himself against the poison of others. Although I have kept watch and ward against all the poisons that one takes with his food, I have not provided against that domestic poison, always the most dangerous to kings, the treachery of army, children, and friends.' Bituitus, thus appealed to, rendered the king the service that he desired.
¬
{Quote_64}
... 'Although I have kept watch and ward against all the poisons that one takes with his food, I have not provided against that domestic poison, always the most dangerous to kings, the treachery of army, children, and friends.'
{Author_64}
Mithridates VI, as quoted by Appianos, The Foreign Wars, The Mithridatic Wars, 16.111

¬ as Poseidonius of Apameia relates in the sixteenth book of his History. Accordingly, when he was slain, he says that Arsakes, when he buried him, said: 'Your courage and your drunkenness have ruined you, O Antiochos; for you hoped that you would be able to drink up the kingdom of Arsakes in your great cups.'
¬
{Quote_65}
... [Poseidonios of Apameia] says that Arsakes [Phraates II], when he buried [Antiochos VII], said 'Your courage and your drunkenness have ruined you, O Antiochos; for you hoped that you would be able to drink up the kingdom of Arsakes in your great cups.'
{Author_65}
Athenaios, Deipnosophistai, 10.54.e

¬ Kleomenes king of Sparta defeated the Argives, of whom more than seven thousand were left dead on the field, and directed his march to Argos, in the hope of making himself master of the city. Then Telesilla, a musician, put herself at the head of the Argive women; they took up arms, and defended the walls so successfully, that they repulsed Kleomenes, and the other king Damaratos, and saved the city. In memory of this exploit of the women, the Argives celebrate a festival at the start of the month of Hermaeus, when the women wear tunics and robes, and the men wear the women's gowns
¬
{Quote_66}
Kleomenes [I] ... directed his march to Argos, ... . Then Telesilla, a musician, put herself at the head of the Argive women; they took up arms, and defended the walls so successfully, that they repulsed Kleomenes, and the other king Damaratos, and saved the city. ...
{Author_66}
Polyainos, Stratagemata, 8.33

¬ Kynane, the daughter of Philippos, was famous for her military knowledge; she commanded armies, and in the field charged at the head of them. In an engagement with the Illyrians, she herself slew their queen with a fatal blow to the throat; and she defeated the Illyrian army with great slaughter. She married Amyntas, son of Perdikkas; and, losing him soon after, never would take a second husband. By Amyntas she had an only daughter named Eurydike: to whom she gave a military education, and instructed her in the science of war. Upon Alexandros's death, his generals parcelled out his dominions among themselves, in exclusion of the royal family. But Kynane crossed the Strymon, forcing her way in the face of Antipatros, who disputed her passage over it. She then passed the Hellespont, to meet the Makedonian army, and Alketas with a powerful force advanced to give her battle. The Makedonians at first paused at the sight of Philippos' daughter, and the sister of Alexandros; but after reproaching Alketas with ingratitude, undaunted at the number of his forces, and his formidable preparations for battle, she bravely advanced to fight against him. She resolved upon a glorious death, rather than, stripped of her dominions, accept a private life, unworthy of the daughter of Philippos.
¬
{Quote_67}
Kynane, the daughter of Philippos [II], was famous for her military knowledge; she commanded armies, and in the field charged at the head of them. In an engagement with the Illyrians, she herself slew their queen ... and she defeated the Illyrian army with great slaughter. ...
{Author_67}
Polyainos, Stratagemata, 8.60

¬ Kynane, the daughter of Philippos, was famous for her military knowledge; she commanded armies, and in the field charged at the head of them. In an engagement with the Illyrians, she herself slew their queen with a fatal blow to the throat; and she defeated the Illyrian army with great slaughter. She married Amyntas, son of Perdikkas; and, losing him soon after, never would take a second husband. By Amyntas she had an only daughter named Eurydike: to whom she gave a military education, and instructed her in the science of war. Upon Alexandros's death, his generals parcelled out his dominions among themselves, in exclusion of the royal family. But Kynane crossed the Strymon, forcing her way in the face of Antipatros, who disputed her passage over it. She then passed the Hellespont, to meet the Makedonian army, and Alketas with a powerful force advanced to give her battle. The Makedonians at first paused at the sight of Philippos' daughter, and the sister of Alexandros; but after reproaching Alketas with ingratitude, undaunted at the number of his forces, and his formidable preparations for battle, she bravely advanced to fight against him. She resolved upon a glorious death, rather than, stripped of her dominions, accept a private life, unworthy of the daughter of Philippos.
¬
{Quote_68}
... Upon Alexandros's death, his generals parcelled out his dominions ... in exclusion of the royal family. But Kynane [daughter of Philippos II] crossed the Strymon, forcing her way in the face of Antipatros ... She then passed the Hellespont, to meet the Makedonian army ...
{Author_68}
Polyainos, Stratagemata, 8.60

¬ Pyrrhos, king of Epirus, was invited by Aristeas the Argive to undertake an expedition against Argos. The Argives assembled in arms at the marketplace; while the women attacked the Epirotes from the house tops with stones and bricks, and forced them to retreat. Pyrrhos himself was killed in the attack, by the blow from a brick, which struck him on the head. The Argive women obtained immortal reputation on this occasion, through the conquest and death of Pyrrhus, who was the most warlike prince of the age.
¬
{Quote_69}
... The Argives assembled in arms at the marketplace; while the women attacked the Epirotes from the house tops with stones and bricks, and forced them to retreat. Pyrrhos himself was killed in the attack, by the blow from a brick, which struck him on the head. ...
{Author_69}
Polyainos, Stratagemata, 8.68

¬ When Ptolemaios made war on the inhabitants of Kyrene, they committed to Lykopos, an Aitolian general, the whole conduct of the war. And while the men engaged in the field of war, the women also took their share of duty: they made the palisades, dug the trenches, supplied the men with missiles, took care of the wounded, and prepared their provisions. The men at length were most of them cut down, and Lycopus changed the constitution into a monarchy; for which the women so censured him with their reproaches, that he ordered many of them to execution, to which they cheerfully and gladly ran.
¬
{Quote_70}
When Ptolemaios made war on ... Kyrene, they committed to Lykopos, an Aitolian general, the whole conduct of the war. ... [And] the women ... made the palisades, dug the trenches, supplied the men with missiles, took care of the wounded, and prepared their provisions. ...
{Author_70}
Polyainos, Stratagemata, 8.70

¬ Rhodogoune was just coming out of her bath, with her hair as yet undressed, when she received intelligence of the revolt of a subject nation. Without waiting to have her hair dressed, she mounted her horse, and put herself at the head of her army. At the same time, she vowed never to have her hair dressed, till she had subdued the rebels; which she eventually achieved after a tedious war. She then bathed, and had her hair dressed. From this circumstance, the seal of the kings of Persia bears on it Rhodogune with dishevelled hair.
¬
{Quote_71}
Rhodogoune [the Seleukid queen] was just coming out of her bath, with her hair as yet undressed, when she received intelligence of the revolt of a subject nation. Without waiting to have her hair dressed, she mounted her horse, and put herself at the head of her army. ...
{Author_71}
Polyainos, Stratagemata, 8.27

¬ When the Macedonians, in close array, stretched out before them their long spears against the target fence which was formed by the close position of their antagonists' shields, and when the Romans, after discharging their javelins without effect, drew their swords, these could neither press on to a closer combat, nor cut off the heads of the spears;
¬
{Quote_72}
When the Macedonians, in close array, stretched out before them their long spears ... and when the Romans, after discharging their javelins without effect, drew their swords, these could neither press on to a closer combat, nor cut off the heads of the spears; ...
{Author_72}
The siege of Atrax, as recorded by Titus Livius, Ab Urbe Condita, 32.17.13

¬ Having arrived at this decision, he ordered the ships of the Achaeans as well as his own to muster at Lechaion; and there he made continual experiments in practising the soldiers of the phalanx to the use of the oar. The Makedonians answered to his instructions with ready enthusiasm; [5] for they are in fact the noblest soldiers on the field of battle, the promptest to undertake service at sea if need be, and the most laborious workers at digging trenches, making palisades, and all such engineering work, in the world:
¬
{Quote_73}
... The Makedonians answered to his instructions with ready enthusiasm; for they are ... the noblest soldiers ..., the promptest to undertake service at sea ... and the most laborious workers at digging trenches, making palisades, and all such engineering work in the world: ...
{Author_73}
Polybios, Histories, 5.2.4-5

¬
¬
{Quote_74}
What can a soldier do who charges when out of breath?
{Author_74}
Vegetius

¬
¬
{Quote_75}
Victory loves prudence
{Author_75}
Latin proverb

¬
¬
{Quote_76}
A dead enemy always smells good
{Author_76}
Alus Vitellus

¬
¬
{Quote_77}
When one side goes against the enemy with the gods' gift of stronger morale, then their adversaries, as a rule, cannot withstand them
{Author_77}
Xenophon

¬
¬
{quote_78}
Only the dead have seen the end of the war
{quoted_79}
Plato

¬
¬
{quote_80}
Veni, vidi, vici
{trans_81}
I came, I saw, I conquered
{quoted_82}
Gaius Julius Caesar

¬
¬
{quote_83}
Silent enim leges inter arma
{trans_84}
Laws are silent in times of war
{quoted_85}
Cicero

¬
¬
{quote_86}
We make war that we may live in peace
{quoted_87}
Aristotle

¬
¬
{quote_88}
Men grow tired of sleep, love, singing and dancing sooner than war
{quoted_89}
Homer

¬
¬
{quote_90}
War spares not the brave but the cowardly
{quoted_91}
Anacreon

¬
¬
{quote_92}
War is sweet to those who have never experienced it
{quoted_93}
Pindar

¬
¬
{quote_94}
In war important events result from trivial causes
{quoted_95}
Gaius Julius Caesar

¬
¬
{quote_96}
Bella detesta matribus
{trans_97}
Wars are the dread of mothers
{quoted_98}
Horace

¬
¬
{quote_99}
Bella, horida bella
{trans_100}
Wars, horrid wars!
{quoted_101}
Virgil

¬
¬
{quote_102}
Willing obedience always beats forced obedience
{quoted_103}
Xenophon

¬
¬
{quote_104}
The fortunes of war are always doubtful
{quoted_105}
Seneca

¬
¬
{quote_106}
The Spartans do not ask how many but where they are
{quoted_107}
Agis II of Sparta

¬
¬
{quote_108}
Come home with this shield or upon it
{quoted_109}
A Spartan woman equips her son

¬
¬
{quote_110}
Valour is superior to numbers
{quoted_111}
Vegetius

¬
¬
{quote_112}
Valour is the contempt of death and pain
{quoted_113}
Tacitus

¬
¬
{quote_114}
To lead untrained people to war is to throw them away
{quoted_115}
Confucius

¬
¬
{quote_116}
In war, truth is the first casualty
{quoted_117}
Aeschylus

¬
¬
{quote_118}
Dulce et decorum est pro patria mori
{trans_119}
It is a sweet and seemly thing to die for one's country
{quoted_120}
Horace

¬
¬
{quote_121}
Qui desiderat pacem praeparet bellum
{trans_122}
Let him who desires peace prepare for war
{quoted_123}
Vegetius

¬
¬
{quote_124}
An ambuscade, if discovered and promptly surrounded, will repay the intended mischief with interest
{quoted_125}
Vegetius

¬
¬
{quote_126}
The blade itself incites to violence
{quoted_127}
Homer

¬
¬
{quote_128}
Who was the first that forged the deadly blade? Of rugged steel his savage soul was made
{quoted_129}
Tibullus

¬
¬
{quote_130}
So ends the bloody business of the day
{quoted_131}
Homer

¬
¬
{quote_132}
Quae caret ora cruore nostro?
{trans_133}
What coast knows not our blood?
{quoted_134}
Horace

¬
¬
{quote_135}
Arms keep peace
{quoted_136}
Latin proverb

¬
¬
{quote_137}
The gods favour the bold
{quoted_138}
Ovid

¬
¬
{quote_139}
Great empires are not maintained by timidity
{quoted_140}
Tacitus

¬
¬
{quote_141}
Fortes fortuna adiuvat
{trans_142}
Fortune favours the brave
{quoted_143}
Terence

¬
¬
{quote_144}
Only the brave enjoy noble and glorious deaths
{quoted_145}
Dionysius of Halicarnassus

¬
¬
{quote_146}
Few men are born brave; many become so through training and force of discipline
{quoted_147}
Vegetius

¬
¬
{quote_148}
Fortis cadere, cedere non potest
{trans_149}
A brave man may fall, but he cannot yield
{quoted_150}
Latin proverb

¬
¬
{quote_151}
In peace, sons bury their fathers; in war, fathers bury their sons
{quoted_152}
Herodotus

¬
¬
{quote_153}
How are the mighty fallen in the midst of battle!
{quoted_154}
II Samuel, I, 25

¬
¬
{quote_155}
The walls shall shake at the noise of the horsemen, and of the wheels, and of the chariots
{quoted_156}
Ezekiel, XXVI, 10

¬
¬
{quote_157}
Alta sedent civilis vulnera dextrae
{trans_158}
Deep are the wounds that civil strife inflicts
{quoted_159}
Lucan

¬
¬
{quote_160}
A collision at sea can ruin your entire day
{quoted_161}
Thucydides

¬
¬
{quote_162}
Fas est et ab hoste doceri
{trans_163}
It is right to learn, even from the enemy
{quoted_164}
Ovid

¬
¬
{quote_165}
Learn to obey before you command
{quoted_166}
Solon of Athens

¬
¬
{quote_167}
March divided and fight concentrated
{quoted_168}
Military maxim

¬
¬
{quote_169}
Divide and conquer
{quoted_170}
Military maxim

¬
¬
{quote_171}
Victi vincimus
{trans_172}
Conquered, we conquer
{quoted_173}
Plautus

¬
¬
{quote_174}
Flet victus, victor interiit
{trans_175}
The conquered mourns, the conqueror is undone
{quoted_176}
Latin proverb

¬
¬
{quote_177}
Courage may be taught as a child is taught to speak
{quoted_178}
Euripides

¬
¬
{quote_179}
Timidi mater non flet
{trans_180}
A coward's mother does not weep
{quoted_181}
Latin proverb

¬
¬
{quote_182}
Danger gleams like sunshine to a brave man's eyes
{quoted_183}
Euripides

¬
¬
{quote_184}
Constant exposure to dangers will breed contempt for them
{quoted_185}
Seneca

¬
¬
{quote_186}
A glorious death is his who for his country falls
{quoted_187}
Homer

¬
¬
{quote_188}
All warfare is based on deception
{quoted_189}
Sun Tzu

¬
¬
{quote_190}
The god of war hates those who hesitate
{quoted_191}
Euripides

¬
¬
{quote_192}
Alea iacta est
{trans_193}
The die is cast
{quoted_194}
Gaius Julius Caesar

¬
¬
{quote_195}
Vae victus
{trans_196}
Woe to the vanquished
{quoted_197}
Livy

¬
¬
{quote_198}
Let all be present and expect the palm, the prize of victory
{quoted_199}
Virgil

¬
¬
{quote_200}
Brave men are a city's strongest tower of defence
{quoted_201}
Alcaeus

¬
¬
{quote_202}
The true contempt of an invader is shown by deeds of valour in the field
{quoted_203}
Hermocrates of Syracuse

¬
¬
{quote_204}
An adversary is more hurt by desertion than by slaughter
{quoted_205}
Vegetius

¬
¬
{quote_206}
Self-control is the chief element in self-respect, and self-respect is the chief element in courage
{quoted_207}
Thucydides

¬
¬
{quote_208}
Cry "Havoc!" and let slip the dogs of war
{quoted_209}
Shakespeare: Julius Caesar, III, 1

¬
¬
{quote_210}
The strong did what they could, and the weak suffered what they must
{quoted_211}
Thucydides

¬
¬
{quote_212}
The sinews of war are infinite money
{quoted_213}
Cicero

¬
¬
{quote_214}
He who knows when he can fight and when he cannot will be victorious
{quoted_215}
Sun Tzu

¬
¬
{quote_216}
The proper arts of a general are judgement and prudence
{quoted_217}
Tacitus

¬
¬
{quote_218}
It is the brave man's part to live with glory, or with glory die
{quoted_219}
Sophocles

¬
¬
{quote_220}
We should provide in peace what we need in war
{quoted_221}
Publilius Syrus

¬
¬
{quote_222}
Generally management of the many is the same as management of the few. It is a matter of organization
{quoted_223}
Sun Tzu

¬
¬
{quote_224}
If a man does not strike first, he will be the first struck
{quoted_225}
Athenogoras of Syracuse

¬
¬
{quote_226}
A wise man in times of peace prepares for war
{quoted_227}
Horace

¬
¬
{quote_228}
In war, numbers alone confer no advantage. Do not advance relying on sheer military power
{quoted_229}
¬+++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++
Sun Tzu

